<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<xml>
  <metadata>
    <source>GILES, 4.358-401</source>
  </metadata>
  <body>
    <page n="GILES v04.p358">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">FI‘ER the interval of a year, Be-</l>
      <l n="3">nedict croeeed the sea into Gaul,</l>
      <l n="4">and no sooner asked than he ob-</l>
      <l n="5"></l>
      <l n="6">tained and carried back with him</l>
      <l n="7"></l>
      <l n="8">.. _. some masons to build him a church</l>
      <l n="9">l" 7 in the Roman style, which he had</l>
      <l n="10">always admired. So much zeal</l>
      <l n="11">did he show from his love to Saint</l>
      <l n="12">Peter, in whose honour he was building it, that within</l>
      <l n="13">a year from the time of laying the foundation, you</l>
      <l n="14">might have seen the roof on and the solemnity of the</l>
      <l n="15">mass celebrated therein. When the work was drawing</l>
      <l n="16">to completion, he sent messengers to Gaul to fetch</l>
      <l n="17">makers of glass, (more properly artiﬁcers,) who were at</l>
      <l n="18">this time unknown in Britain, that they might glaze</l>
      <l n="19">the windows of his church, with the cloisters and dining-</l>
      <l n="20">rooms. This was done, and they came, and not only</l>
      <l n="21">ﬁnished the work required, but taught the English</l>
      <l n="22">nation their handicraft, which was well adapted for en—</l>
      <l n="23">closing the lanterns of the church, and for the vessels</l>
      <l n="24">required for various uses. All other things necessary</l>
      <l n="25">for the service of the church and the altar, the sacred</l>
      <l n="26">vessels, and the vestments, because they could not be</l>
      <l n="27">procured in England, he took especial care to buy and</l>
      <l n="28">bring home from foreign parts. ,</l>
      <l n="29"></l>
      <l n="30">. OME decorations and muniments</l>
      <l n="31"></l>
      <l n="32">there were which could not be pro-</l>
      <l n="33"></l>
      <l n="34">_ cured even in Gaul, and these the</l>
      <l n="35"></l>
      <l n="36">, .3 pious founder determined to fetch</l>
      <l n="37"></l>
      <l n="38">x, [A , from Rome , for which purpose,</l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40">SA ,</l>
      <l n="41">voyage to Rome, and returned</l>
      <l n="42">loaded with more abundant spiritual merchandise than</l>
      <l n="43">before. In the ﬁrst place, he brought back a large</l>
      <l n="44">quantity of books of all kinds ; secondly, a great num-</l>
      <l n="45"></l>
      <l n="46"></l>
      <l n="47"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p359">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">quod reliquiarum beatorum Apostolorum martyrumque</l>
      <l n="3">Christi abundantem gratiam multis Anglorum ecclesiis</l>
      <l n="4">profuturam advexit; tertio, quod ordinem cantandi,</l>
      <l n="5">psallendi, atque in ecclesia ministrandi, juxta morem</l>
      <l n="6">Romanæ institutionis suo monasterio coutradidit, postu-</l>
      <l n="7">lato videlicet atque accepto ab Agathone papa archican—</l>
      <l n="8">tore ecclesiæ beati Apostoli Petri et abbate monasterii</l>
      <l n="9">beati Martini Joanne, quem sui futurum magistrum</l>
      <l n="10">monasterii Britannias, Romanum Anglis adduceret.</l>
      <l n="11">Qui illo perveniens, non solum viva voce, quæ Romæ</l>
      <l n="12">didicit, ecclesiastica. discentibus tradidit; sed et non</l>
      <l n="13">pauca etiam literis mandata reliquit, quæ hactenus in</l>
      <l n="14">ejusdem monasterii bibliotheca memoriæ gratia ser-</l>
      <l n="15">vantur. Quartum, Benedictus non vile munus attulit,</l>
      <l n="16">epistolam privilegii a venerabili papa Agathone cum</l>
      <l n="17">licentia, consensu, desiderio, et hortatu ngridi regis ac-</l>
      <l n="18">ceptam, qua. monasterium, quod fecit, ab omni prorsus</l>
      <l n="19">extrinseca irruptione tutum perpetuo redderetur ac</l>
      <l n="20">liberum. Quintum, picturas imaginum sanctarum,</l>
      <l n="21">quas ad omandum ecclesiam beati Petri Apostoli, quam</l>
      <l n="22">construxerat, detulit; imaginem, videlicet, beatæ Dei</l>
      <l n="23">Genetricis semperque virginis Mariæ, simul et duodecim</l>
      <l n="24">Apostolorum, quibus mediam ejusdem ecclesiæ testu-</l>
      <l n="25">dinem, ducto a pariete ad parietem tabulato, præcin-</l>
      <l n="26">geret ; imagines evangelicæ historiæ, quibus australem</l>
      <l n="27">ecclesiæ parietem decoraret; imagines visionum Apo-</l>
      <l n="28">calypsis beati Johannis, quibus septentrionalem æque</l>
      <l n="29">parietem ornaret, quatenus intrantes ecclesiam omnes,</l>
      <l n="30">etiam literarum ignari, quaquaversum intenderent, vel</l>
      <l n="31">semper amabilem Christi sanctorumque ejus, quamvis</l>
      <l n="32">in imagine, contemplarentur aspectum; vel Dominicæ</l>
      <l n="33">incarnationis gratiam vigilantiore mente recolerent; vel</l>
      <l n="34">extremi discrimen examinis quasi coram oculis habentes,</l>
      <l n="35">districtius se ipsi examinare meminissent.</l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37"></l>
      <l n="38"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p360">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">ber of relics of Christ’s Apostles and martyrs, all likely</l>
      <l n="3">to bring a blessing on many an English church; thirdly,</l>
      <l n="4">he introduced the Roman mode of chanting, singing,</l>
      <l n="5">and ministering in the church, by obtaining permission</l>
      <l n="6">from Pope Agatho to take back with him John, the</l>
      <l n="7">archchanter of the church of St. Peter, and abbot of the</l>
      <l n="8">monastery of St. Martin, to teach the English. This</l>
      <l n="9">J ohn, when he arrived in England, not only communi-</l>
      <l n="10">cated instruction by teaching personally, but left he-</l>
      <l n="11">hind him numerous writings, which are still preserved</l>
      <l n="12">in the library of the same monastery. In the fourth</l>
      <l n="13">place, Benedict brought with him a thing by no means</l>
      <l n="14">to be despised, namely, a letter of privilege from Pope</l>
      <l n="15">Agatha, which he had procured, not only With the</l>
      <l n="16">consent, but by the request and exhortation, of King</l>
      <l n="17">ngrid, and by which the monastery was rendered</l>
      <l n="18">safe and secure for ever from foreign invasion. Fifthly,</l>
      <l n="19">he brought with him pictures of sacred representations,</l>
      <l n="20">to adorn the church of St. Peter, which he had built;</l>
      <l n="21">namely, a likeness of the Virgin Mary and of the</l>
      <l n="22">twelve Apostles, with which he intended to adorn the</l>
      <l n="23">central nave, on boarding placed from one wall to the</l>
      <l n="24">other; also some ﬁgures from ecclesiastical history for</l>
      <l n="25">the south wall, and others from the Revelation of St.</l>
      <l n="26">J ohn for the north wall; so that every one who entered</l>
      <l n="27">the church,.even if they could not read, wherever they</l>
      <l n="28">turned their eyes, might have before them the amiable</l>
      <l n="29">countenance of Christ and his saints, though it were</l>
      <l n="30">but in a picture, and with watchful minds might re-</l>
      <l n="31">volve on the beneﬁts of our Lord’s incarnation, and</l>
      <l n="32">having before their eyes the perils of the last judgment,</l>
      <l n="33">might examine their hearts the more strictly on that</l>
      <l n="34">account.</l>
      <l n="35"></l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p361">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">GITUR venerabilis Benedicti vir-</l>
      <l n="3">tute, industria, ac religione, rex</l>
      <l n="4">ngridus non minimum delectatus,</l>
      <l n="5">terram, quam ad construendum</l>
      <l n="6">monasterium ei donaverat, quia</l>
      <l n="7">bene se ac fructuose ordinatum</l>
      <l n="8">esse conspexit, quadraginta adhuc</l>
      <l n="9">familiarum data possessione, aug-</l>
      <l n="10">mentare curavit; ubi post annum, missis monachis</l>
      <l n="11">numero ferme decem et septem, et præposito abbate ac</l>
      <l n="12">presbytero, Ceolfrido, Benedictus consultu, immo etiam</l>
      <l n="13">jussu, præfati ngridi regis, monasterium beati Apostoli</l>
      <l n="14">Pauli construxit, ea duntaxat ratione, ut una utriusque</l>
      <l n="15">loci pax et concordia, eadem perpetua familiaritas con-</l>
      <l n="16">servaretur et gratia; ut, sicut verbi gratia, corpus a</l>
      <l n="17">capite per quod spirat non potest avelli, caput corporis</l>
      <l n="18">sine quo non vivit nequit oblivisci, ita nullus hæc</l>
      <l n="19">monasteria, primarum Apostolorum fraterna. societate</l>
      <l n="20">conjuncta, aliquo ab invicem tentaret disturbare conatu.</l>
      <l n="21">Ceolfridus autem hic, quem abbatem constituit Bene-</l>
      <l n="22">dictus, a primis instituti monasterii prioris exordiis</l>
      <l n="23">adjutor illi per omnia strenuissimus aderat, et cum eo</l>
      <l n="24">tempore congruo Romam discendi necessaria simul et</l>
      <l n="25">adorandi gratia adierat. Quo tempore etiam presby-</l>
      <l n="26">terum Easterwinum de monasterio beati Petri eligens</l>
      <l n="27">abbatem, eidem monasterio regendi jure praefecit; ut</l>
      <l n="28">quem solus non poterat laborem, socia dilectissimi</l>
      <l n="29">commilitonis virtute levius ferret. Nec ab re videatur</l>
      <l n="30">cuiquam duos unum monasterium simul habuisse ab-</l>
      <l n="31">bates. Fecit hoc frequens illius pro monasterii utilitate</l>
      <l n="32">profectio, creber trans oceanum egressus incertusque</l>
      <l n="33">regressus. Nam et beatissimum Petrum Apostolum</l>
      <l n="34">Romæ pontifices sub se duos per ordinem ad regendam</l>
      <l n="35">ecclesiam constituisse, causa instante necessaria., tradunt</l>
      <l n="36">historiae; et ipse Magnus abbas Benedictus, sicut de</l>
      <l n="37">illo beatus papa Gregorius scribit, duodecim abbates</l>
      <l n="38">suis discipulis, prout utile judicavit, sine caritatis</l>
      <l n="39">detrimento, immo pro augmento caritatis, præfecit;</l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41"></l>
      <l n="42"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p362">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">Thus King ngrid, delighted by the virtues and</l>
      <l n="3">zealous piety of the venerable Benedict, augmented the</l>
      <l n="4">territory Which he had given, on Which to build this</l>
      <l n="5">monastery, by a further grant of land of forty hides; on</l>
      <l n="6">which, at the end of a year, Benedict, by the same King</l>
      <l n="7">ngrid’s concurrence, and, indeed, command, built the</l>
      <l n="8">monastery of the Apostle St. Paul, with this condition,</l>
      <l n="9">that the same concord and unity should exist for ever</l>
      <l n="10">between the two ; so that, for instance, as the body</l>
      <l n="11">cannot be separated from the head, nor the head forget</l>
      <l n="12">the body by which it lives, in the same manner no</l>
      <l n="13">man. should ever try to divide these two monasteries,</l>
      <l n="14">yvhich had been united under the names of the ﬁrst of</l>
      <l n="15">the Apostles. Ceolfrid, whom Benedict made abbot,</l>
      <l n="16">had been his most zealous assistant from the ﬁrst found-</l>
      <l n="17">ation of the former monastery, and had gone with him</l>
      <l n="18">at the proper time to Rome, for the sake of acquiring</l>
      <l n="19">instruction, and offering up his prayers. At which time</l>
      <l n="20">also he chose priest Easterwine to be the abbot of St.</l>
      <l n="21">Peter’s monastery, that with the help of this fellow-sol-</l>
      <l n="22">dier he might sustain a burden otherwise too heavy for</l>
      <l n="23">him. And let no one think it unbecoming that one</l>
      <l n="24">monastery should have two abbots at once. His fre-</l>
      <l n="25">_quent travelling for the beneﬁt of the monastery, and</l>
      <l n="26">absence in foreign parts, was the cause; and history</l>
      <l n="27">informs us, that, on a pressing occasion, the blessed St.</l>
      <l n="28">Peter also ordained two pontiﬁ's under him to rule the</l>
      <l n="29">Church at Rome; and Abbot Benedict the Great, him-</l>
      <l n="30">self, as Pope St. Gregory writes of him, appointed</l>
      <l n="31">twelve abbots over his followers, as he judged expe-</l>
      <l n="32">dient, without any harm done to Christian charity;</l>
      <l n="33">nay, rather to the increase thereof.</l>
      <l n="34"></l>
      <l n="35"></l>
      <l n="36"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p363">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">Suscepit igitur memoratus vir curam monasterii re-</l>
      <l n="3">gendi, nono, ex qua fundamentum est, anno. Perman-</l>
      <l n="4">sit in eo usque ad obitum suum annis quatuor, vir</l>
      <l n="5">nobilis, sed insigne nobilitatis non ad jactantiæ mate-</l>
      <l n="6">riem, ut quidam, despectumque aliorum, sed ad majorem,</l>
      <l n="7">ut Dei servum decet, animi nobilitatem convertens. Pa-</l>
      <l n="8">truelis quippe erat abbatis sui Benedicti, sed amborum</l>
      <l n="9">tanta mentis ingenuitas, talis mundanæ ingenuitatis fuit</l>
      <l n="10">pro nihilo contemtus, ut neque iste monasterium in-</l>
      <l n="11">gressus, aliquem sibi præ ceteris ob intuitum consan-</l>
      <l n="12">guinitatis aut nobilitatis honorem quærendum, neque</l>
      <l n="13">ille putaret offerendum; sed æquali cum fratribus lance</l>
      <l n="14">boni propositi juvenis gloriabatur se regularem per</l>
      <l n="15">omnia servare disciplinam. Et quidem cum fuisset</l>
      <l n="16">minister ngridi regis, relictis semel negotiis seculari-</l>
      <l n="17">bus, depositis armis, assumta militia spirituali tantum,</l>
      <l n="18">mansit humilis, fratrumque simillimus aliorum, ut ven-</l>
      <l n="19">tilare cum eis et triturare, oves vitulasque mulgere, in</l>
      <l n="20">pistrino, in horto, in coquina, in cunctis monasterii</l>
      <l n="21">operibus, jucundus et obediens gauderet exerceri. Sed</l>
      <l n="22">et abbatis nomine graduque assumto, eodem animo quo</l>
      <l n="23">prius manebat ad omnes, juxta id quod quidam sapiens</l>
      <l n="24">admonet, dicens, ‘Rectorem te constituerunt, noli ex-</l>
      <l n="25">tolli, sed esto in illis, quasi unus ex illis, mitis, affabilis,</l>
      <l n="26">et benignus omnibus., Et quidem, ubi opportunum</l>
      <l n="27">comperiebat, peccantes regulari disciplina coercens, sed</l>
      <l n="28">magis tamen ingenita diligendi consuetudine sedulus</l>
      <l n="29">admonens, ne quis peccare vellet, et limpidissimam vul-</l>
      <l n="30">tus ejus lucem nubilo sibi suæ inquietudinis abscondere.</l>
      <l n="31">Sæpe pro curandis monasterii negotiis alicubi digrediens,</l>
      <l n="32">ubi operantes invenit fratres, solebat eis confestim in</l>
      <l n="33"></l>
      <l n="34"></l>
      <l n="35"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p364">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">HIS mun therefore undertook the</l>
      <l n="3"></l>
      <l n="4">' government of the monastery in</l>
      <l n="5"></l>
      <l n="6">), the ninth year after its foundation,</l>
      <l n="7"></l>
      <l n="8">" and continued it till his death four</l>
      <l n="9"></l>
      <l n="10">years after. He was a man of</l>
      <l n="11"></l>
      <l n="12">noble birth ; but he did not make</l>
      <l n="13"></l>
      <l n="14">that, like some mon, a cause Of</l>
      <l n="15"></l>
      <l n="16">boasting and dcspising others, but</l>
      <l n="17"></l>
      <l n="18">a motive for exercising nobility of mind also, as be-</l>
      <l n="19">comes a servant of the Lord. He was the cousin of his</l>
      <l n="20">own abbot Benedict; and yet such was the singleness</l>
      <l n="21">of mind in both, such their contempt for human gran-</l>
      <l n="22">deur, that the one, on entering the monastery, did not</l>
      <l n="23">expect any notice of honour or relationship to be taken</l>
      <l n="24">of him more than of others, and Benedict himself never</l>
      <l n="25">thought of offering any; but the young man, faring</l>
      <l n="26">like the rest, took pleasure in undergoing the usual</l>
      <l n="27">course of monastic discipline in every respect. And</l>
      <l n="28">indeed, though he had been an attendant on King</l>
      <l n="29">ngrid, and had abandoued his temporal vocation and</l>
      <l n="30">arms, devoting himself to spiritual warfare, he remained</l>
      <l n="31">so humble and like the other brethren, that he took</l>
      <l n="32">pleasure in threshing and winnowing, milking the ewes</l>
      <l n="33">and cows, and employed himself in the bakehouse, the</l>
      <l n="34">garden, the kitchen, and in all the other labours of the</l>
      <l n="35">monastery with readiness and submission. When he</l>
      <l n="36">attained to the name and dignity of abbot, be retained</l>
      <l n="37">the same spirit; saying to all, according to the advice</l>
      <l n="38">of a certain wise man, “ They have made thee a ruler ;</l>
      <l n="39">be not exalted, but be amongst them like one of them,</l>
      <l n="40">gentle, affable, and kind to all.” Whenever occasion</l>
      <l n="41">required, he punished oﬁ'enders by regular discipline;</l>
      <l n="42">but was rather careful, out of his natural habits of love,</l>
      <l n="43">to warn them not to offend and bring a cloud of dis-</l>
      <l n="44">quietude over his cheerful countenance. Oftentimel,</l>
      <l n="45">when he went forth on the business of the monastery,</l>
      <l n="46">if he found the brethren working, he would join them</l>
      <l n="47"></l>
      <l n="48"></l>
      <l n="49"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p365">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">opere conjungi; .vel aratri gressum stiva regendo, vel</l>
      <l n="3">ferrum malleo domanda, vel ventilabrum" manu concu-</l>
      <l n="4">tiendo, vel aliud quid tale gerendo. Erat enim et viribus</l>
      <l n="5">fortis juvenis, et lingua suavis; sed et animo hilaris, et</l>
      <l n="6">beneficio largus, et honestus aspectu. Eodem quo fra-</l>
      <l n="7">tres ceteri cibo, semper eadem vescebatur in domo, ipso</l>
      <l n="8">quo prius quam abbas esset communi dormiebat in loco,</l>
      <l n="9">adeo ut et morbo correptus et obitus sui certis ex signis</l>
      <l n="10">jam præscius, duos adhuc dies in dormitorio fratrum</l>
      <l n="11">quiesceret. Nam quinque reliquos usque ad exitus ho-</l>
      <l n="12">ram dies in secretiori se æde locabat; qua die quadam</l>
      <l n="13">egrediens, et sub divo residens, accitis ad se fratribus</l>
      <l n="14">cunctis, more naturæ misericordis osculum pacis eis</l>
      <l n="15">flentibus ac de abscessu tanti patris et pastoris moeren-</l>
      <l n="16">tibus dedit. Obiit autem per nonas Martias, noctu,</l>
      <l n="17">fratribus matutinæ psalmodiæ laude vacantibus. Viginti</l>
      <l n="18">quatuor annorum erat cum monasterium peteret, duo-</l>
      <l n="19">decim in eo vixit annis, septem presbyteram functus</l>
      <l n="20">est annis, quatuor ex eis monasterii regimen agebat; ac</l>
      <l n="21"></l>
      <l n="22">sic terrenos artus moribundaque membra relinquens,</l>
      <l n="23">cælestia regna petivit. '</l>
      <l n="24"></l>
      <l n="25">Verum his de vita venerabilis Easterwini breviter</l>
      <l n="26">prælibatis, redeamus ad ordinem narrandi. Constituto</l>
      <l n="27">illo abbate Benedictus monasterio beati Petri Apostoli,</l>
      <l n="28">constituto et Ceolfrido monasterio beati Pauli, non multo</l>
      <l n="29">post temporis spatio quinta vice de Britannia Romam</l>
      <l n="30">accurrens, innumeris (sicut semper) ecclesiasticarum</l>
      <l n="31">donis commodorum locupletatus rediit; magna quidem</l>
      <l n="32">copia voluminum sacrorum; sed non minori (sicut et</l>
      <l n="33">prius) sanctarum imaginum munere ditatus. Nam et</l>
      <l n="34">tunc Divinæ historiæ picturas, quibus totam beatæ Dei</l>
      <l n="35">Genetricis, quam in monasterio majore fecerat, eccle-</l>
      <l n="36">siam in gyro coronaret, attulit; imagines quoque ad</l>
      <l n="37">ornandum monasterium ecclesiamque beati Pauli Apo-</l>
      <l n="38"></l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p366">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">and work with them, by taking the plough-handle, or</l>
      <l n="3">handling the smith’s hammer, or using the winnowing</l>
      <l n="4">machine, or any thing of like nature. For he was a</l>
      <l n="5">young man of great strength, and pleasant tone of</l>
      <l n="6">voice, of a. kind and bountiful disposition, and fair to</l>
      <l n="7">look on. He ate of the same food as the other bre-</l>
      <l n="8">thren, and in the same apartment: he slept in the same</l>
      <l n="9">common room as he did before he was abbot ; so that</l>
      <l n="10">even after he was taken ill, and foresaw clear signs of</l>
      <l n="11">his approaching death, he still remained two days in the</l>
      <l n="12">common dormitory of the brethren. He passed the ﬁve</l>
      <l n="13">days immediame before his death in a private apart-</l>
      <l n="14">ment, from which he came out one day, and sitting in</l>
      <l n="15">the open air, sent for all the brethren, and, as his kind</l>
      <l n="16">feelings prompted him, gave to each of them the kiss of</l>
      <l n="17">peace, whilst they all shed tears of sorrow for the loss</l>
      <l n="18">of this their father and their guide. He died on the</l>
      <l n="19">seventh of March, in the night, as the brethren were</l>
      <l n="20">leaving off the matin hymn. He was twenty—four years</l>
      <l n="21">old when he entered the monastery; he lived there</l>
      <l n="22">twelve years, during seven of which he was in priest’s</l>
      <l n="23">orders, the others he passed in the dignity of abbot;</l>
      <l n="24">and so, having thrown off his ﬂeshly and perishable</l>
      <l n="25">body, he entered the heavenly kingdom.</l>
      <l n="26"></l>
      <l n="27">Now that we have had this foretaste of the life of the</l>
      <l n="28">venerable Easterwine, let us resume the thread of the</l>
      <l n="29">narrative. When Benedict had made this man abbot</l>
      <l n="30">of St. Peter’s, and Ceolfrid abbot of St. Paul’s, he not</l>
      <l n="31">long after made his ﬁfth voyage from Britain to Rome,</l>
      <l n="32">and returned (as usual) with an immense number of</l>
      <l n="33">proper ecclesiastical relics. There were many sacred</l>
      <l n="34">books and pictures of the saints, as numerous as before.</l>
      <l n="35">He also brought with him pictures out of our Lord’s</l>
      <l n="36">history, which he hung round the chapel of Our Lady</l>
      <l n="37">in the larger monastery; and others to adorn St. Paul’s</l>
      <l n="38">church and monastery, ably describing the connexion</l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p367">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">stoli, de concordia Veteris et Novi Testamenti summa</l>
      <l n="3">ratione compositas, exhibuit; verbi gratia, Isaac ligna,</l>
      <l n="4">quibus immolaretur, portantem, et Dominum crucem,</l>
      <l n="5">in qua pateretur, æque portantem, proxima super invi-</l>
      <l n="6">cem regione, pictura conjunxit. Item, serpenti in eremo</l>
      <l n="7">a Moyse exaltato, Filium hominis in cruce exaltatum</l>
      <l n="8">comparavit. Attulit inter alia, et pallia duo holoserica</l>
      <l n="9">incomparaudi operis, quibus postea ab Alfrido rege</l>
      <l n="10">ejusque consiliariis, namque ngridum postquam rediit</l>
      <l n="11">jam interfectum reperit, terram trium familiarum ad</l>
      <l n="12">austrum Wiri fluminis juxta ostium, comparavit.</l>
      <l n="13"></l>
      <l n="14">Verum inter læta quæ veniens attulit, tristia domi re-</l>
      <l n="15">perit; venerabilem videlicet presbyterum Easterwinum,</l>
      <l n="16">quem abiturus abbatem constituerat, simul et fratrum</l>
      <l n="17">ei commissurum catervam non paucam, per cuncta gras-</l>
      <l n="18">sante pestilentia, jam migrasse de seculo. Sed aderat</l>
      <l n="19">et solamen, quia. in loco Easterwini virum æque reve-</l>
      <l n="20">rendissimum ac mitissimum de monasterio eodem, Sib-</l>
      <l n="21">fridum videlicet diaconum, electione fratrum suorum</l>
      <l n="22">simul et coabbatis ejus Ceolfridi, mox substitutum cog-</l>
      <l n="23">novit; virum scientia quidem Scripturarum sufficienter</l>
      <l n="24">instructum, moribus optimis ornatum, mira abstinentiæ</l>
      <l n="25">virtute præditum, sed ad custodiam virtutum animi</l>
      <l n="26">corporis infirmitate non minime depressum, ad conser-</l>
      <l n="27">vandam cordis innocentiam nocivo et irremediabili pul-</l>
      <l n="28">monum vitio laborantem.</l>
      <l n="29"></l>
      <l n="30">Nec multo post etiam Benedictus ipse morbo ccepit</l>
      <l n="31">ingruente fatigari. Ut enim tantam religionis instan-</l>
      <l n="32">tiam etiam patientiæ virtus adjuncta probaret, Divina</l>
      <l n="33">utrumque pietas temporali ægritudine postravit in lec-</l>
      <l n="34">tum; ut post aegritudinem morte devictam perpetum</l>
      <l n="35">supernæ pacis et lucis quiete refoveret. Nam et Sig-</l>
      <l n="36">fridus, ut diximus, longa interiorum molestia castigatus</l>
      <l n="37">diem pervenit ad ultimum. Et Benedictus, per trien-</l>
      <l n="38"></l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p368">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">of the Old and New Testament ; as, for instance, Isaac</l>
      <l n="3">bearing the wood for his own sacriﬁce, and Christ car-</l>
      <l n="4">rying the cross on which he was about to suffer, were</l>
      <l n="5">placed side by side. Again, the serpent raised up by</l>
      <l n="6">Moses in the desert was illustrated by the Son of Man</l>
      <l n="7">exalted on the cross. Among other things, he brought</l>
      <l n="8">two cloaks, all of silk, and of incomparable workman-</l>
      <l n="9">ship, for which he received an estate of three hides on</l>
      <l n="10">the south bank of the river Were, near its mouth, from</l>
      <l n="11">King Alfrid, for he found on his return that ngrid</l>
      <l n="12">had been murdered during his absence.</l>
      <l n="13"></l>
      <l n="14">UT, amid this prosperity, he found</l>
      <l n="15">\‘ afﬂictions also awaiting his return.</l>
      <l n="16">The venerable Easterwine, whom</l>
      <l n="17">’ he had made abbot when be de-</l>
      <l n="18">; parted, and many of the brethren</l>
      <l n="19">"' committed to his care, had died of</l>
      <l n="20"></l>
      <l n="21">a general pestilence. But for this</l>
      <l n="22"></l>
      <l n="23">loss he found some consolation in</l>
      <l n="24">the good and reverend deacon, Sigfrid, whom the bre-</l>
      <l n="25">thren and his co-abbot Ceolfrid had chosen to be his</l>
      <l n="26">successor. He was a man Well skilled in the know-</l>
      <l n="27">ledge of Holy Scripture, of most excellent manners, of</l>
      <l n="28">wonderful continence, and one in whom the virtues of</l>
      <l n="29">the mind were in no small degree depressed by bodily</l>
      <l n="30">inﬁrmity, and the innocency of whose heart was tem-</l>
      <l n="31">pered with a baneful and incurable aﬂ'ection of the</l>
      <l n="32">lungs.</l>
      <l n="33"></l>
      <l n="34">Not long after, Benedict himself was seized by a</l>
      <l n="35">disease. For, that the virtue of patience might be a</l>
      <l n="36">trial of their religious zeal, the Divine Love laid both of</l>
      <l n="37">them on the bed of temporal sickness, that when they</l>
      <l n="38">had conquered their sorrows by death, He might cherish</l>
      <l n="39">them for ever in heavenly peace and quietude. For</l>
      <l n="40">Sigfrid also, as I have mentioned, died wasted by a long</l>
      <l n="41">illness: and Benedict died of a palsy, which grew upon</l>
      <l n="42"></l>
      <l n="43">B b</l>
      <l n="44"></l>
      <l n="45"></l>
      <l n="46"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p369">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">nium languore paulatim accrescente, tanta paralysi dis-</l>
      <l n="3">solutus est, ut ab omni prorsus inferiorum membrorum</l>
      <l n="4">factus sit parte præmortuus, superioribus solum, sine</l>
      <l n="5">quorum vita vivere nequit homo, ad officium patientiæ</l>
      <l n="6">virtutumque reservatis, studebant in dolore semper</l>
      <l n="7">Auctori gratias referre, semper Dei laudibus fratemisve</l>
      <l n="8">hortatibus vacare. Agebat Benedictus advenientes</l>
      <l n="9">saepius ad se fratres de custödienda, quam statuerat,</l>
      <l n="10">Regula firmare; ‘ Neque enim putare habetis,, inquit,</l>
      <l n="11">‘ quod ex meo hæc, quæ vobis statui, decreta indoctus</l>
      <l n="12">corde protulerim. Ex decem quippe et septem monas-</l>
      <l n="13">teriis, quæ inter longos meæ crebræ peregrinationis dis-</l>
      <l n="14">cursus optima comperi, hæc universa didici, et vobis</l>
      <l n="15">salubriter observanda contradidi.’ Bibliothecam, quam</l>
      <l n="16">de Roma nobilissimam copiosissimamque advexerat, ad</l>
      <l n="17">instructionem ecclesiæ necessariam, sollicite servari in-</l>
      <l n="18">tegram, nec per incuriam foedati, aut passim dissipari</l>
      <l n="19">præcepit. Sed et hoc sedulus eisdem solebat iterare</l>
      <l n="20">mandatum, ne quis in electione abbatis, generis prosa-</l>
      <l n="21">piam, et non magis vivendi docendique probitatem,</l>
      <l n="22">putaret esse quærendum. ‘ Et vere,’ inquit, ‘ dico vobis,</l>
      <l n="23">quia in comparatione duorum malorum, tolerabilius mihi</l>
      <l n="24">multo est totum hunc locum, in quo monasterium feci,</l>
      <l n="25">si sic judicaverit Deus, in solitudinem sempiternam</l>
      <l n="26">redigi, quam ut frater meus carnalis, quem novimus</l>
      <l n="27">viam veritatis non ingredi, in eo regendo post me ab-</l>
      <l n="28">batis nomine succedat. Ideoque multum cavetote,</l>
      <l n="29">fratres, semper, ne secundum genus unquam, ne deforis</l>
      <l n="30">aliunde, vobis patrem quæratis ; sed juxta quod Regula</l>
      <l n="31">magni quondam abbatis Benedicti, juxta quod privilegii</l>
      <l n="32">nostri continent decreta, in conventu vestræ congrega-</l>
      <l n="33">tionis communi consilio perquiratis, qui secundum vitæ</l>
      <l n="34">meritum et sapientiæ doctrinam aptior ad tale ministe-</l>
      <l n="35">rium perficiendum digniorque probetur; et quemcunque</l>
      <l n="36">omnes unanimæ caritatis inquisitione optimum cog-</l>
      <l n="37">noscentes elegeritis, hunc vobis, accito episcopo, rogetis</l>
      <l n="38">abbatem consueta benedictione ﬁrmari. Nam qui car-</l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p370">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">him for three whole years; so that when he was dead in</l>
      <l n="3">all his lower extremities, his upper and vital members,</l>
      <l n="4">spared to show his patience and virtue, were employed</l>
      <l n="5">in the midst of his sufferings in giving thanks to the</l>
      <l n="6">Author of his being, in praises to God, and exhorta-</l>
      <l n="7">tions to the brethren. He urged the brethren, when</l>
      <l n="8">they came to see him, to observe the rule which he had</l>
      <l n="9">given them. “ For,” said he, “ you cannot suppose that</l>
      <l n="10">it was my own untaught heart which dictated this rule</l>
      <l n="11">to you. I learnt it from seventeen monasteries, which</l>
      <l n="12">I saw during my travels, and most approved of, and I</l>
      <l n="13">copied these institutions thence for your beneﬁt.” The</l>
      <l n="14">large and noble library, which he had brought from</l>
      <l n="15">Rome, and which was necessary for the ediﬁcation of</l>
      <l n="16">his church, he commanded to be kept entire, and neither</l>
      <l n="17">by neglect to be injured or dispersed. But on one point</l>
      <l n="18">he was most solicitous, in choosing an abbot, lest high</l>
      <l n="19">birth, and not rather probity of life and doctrine, should</l>
      <l n="20">be attended to. “And I tell you of a truth,” said he,</l>
      <l n="21">“ in the choice of two evils, it would be much more</l>
      <l n="22">tolerable for me, if God so pleased, that this place,</l>
      <l n="23">wherein I have built the monastery, should for ever</l>
      <l n="24">become a desert, than that my carnal brother, who, as</l>
      <l n="25">we know, walks not in the way of truth, should become</l>
      <l n="26">abbot, and succeed me in its government. Wherefore,</l>
      <l n="27">my brethren, beware, and never choose an abbot on</l>
      <l n="28"></l>
      <l n="29">account of his birth, nor from any foreign place; but</l>
      <l n="30">seek out, according to the rule of Abbot Benedict the</l>
      <l n="31"></l>
      <l n="32">Great, and the decrees of our order, with common con-</l>
      <l n="33">sent, from amongst your own company, whoever in</l>
      <l n="34">virtue of life and wisdom of doctrine may be found ﬁt-</l>
      <l n="35">test for this ofﬁce; and whomsoever you shall, by this</l>
      <l n="36">unanimous inquiry of Christian charity, prefer and</l>
      <l n="37">choose, let him be made abbot with the customary</l>
      <l n="38">blessings, in presence of the bishop. For those who</l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40">Bb2</l>
      <l n="41"></l>
      <l n="42"></l>
      <l n="43"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p371">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">nali,’ inquit, ‘ ordine camales ﬁlios generant, carnali</l>
      <l n="3">necesse est ac terrenæ suæ hæreditati carnales ter-</l>
      <l n="4">renosque quærant heredes ; at qui spirituales Deo ﬁlios</l>
      <l n="5">spirituali semine Verbi procreant, spiritualia oportet</l>
      <l n="6">sint cuncta, quæ agunt. Inter spirituales suos liberos</l>
      <l n="7">eum majorem, qui ampliori Spiritus gratia sit præditus,</l>
      <l n="8">æstiment; quomodo terreni parentes, quem primum</l>
      <l n="9">partu fuderint, eum principium' liberorum suorum cog-</l>
      <l n="10">noscere, et ceteris in partienda sua hereditate præferen-</l>
      <l n="11">dum ducere solent.,</l>
      <l n="12"></l>
      <l n="13">Neque hoc reticendam, quod venerabilis abbas Bene—</l>
      <l n="14">dictus ad temperandum sæpe longæ noctis tædium,</l>
      <l n="15">quam præ inﬁrmitatis onere ducebat insomnem, advo-</l>
      <l n="16">cato lectore, vel exemplar patientiæ J 0b, vel aliud quid</l>
      <l n="17">Scripturarum quo consolaretur ægrotus, quo depressus</l>
      <l n="18">in infimis vivacius ad superna erigeretur, coram se re-</l>
      <l n="19">citari jubebat. Et quia nullatenus ad orandum surgere,</l>
      <l n="20"></l>
      <l n="21">non facile ad explendum solitæ Psalmodiæ cursum lin-</l>
      <l n="22">guam vocemve poterat levare, didicit vir prudens, affectu</l>
      <l n="23">religionis dictante, per singulas diurnæ sive nocturnæ</l>
      <l n="24">orationis horas, aliquos ad se fratrum vocare, quibus</l>
      <l n="25">Psalmos consuetos duobus in choris resonantibus, et</l>
      <l n="26">ipse cum eis quatenus poterat psallendo, quod per se</l>
      <l n="27">solum nequiverat, eorum juvamine suppleret.</l>
      <l n="28"></l>
      <l n="29">T ubi uterque abbas lassatus in-</l>
      <l n="30"></l>
      <l n="31">firmitate diutina, jam se morti</l>
      <l n="32"></l>
      <l n="33">vicinum, nec regendo monasterio</l>
      <l n="34"></l>
      <l n="35">~‘ ‘ idoneum fore conspexit; tanta</l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37">namque eos affecit inﬁrmitas car-</l>
      <l n="38"></l>
      <l n="39">." nis, ut perficeretur in eis virtus</l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41">Christi, ut cum quadam die desi-</l>
      <l n="42"></l>
      <l n="43">derantibus eis se invicem, prius-</l>
      <l n="44"></l>
      <l n="45">quam de hoc seculo migrarent, videre et alloqui, Sigfri-</l>
      <l n="46">due in feretro deportaretur ad cubiculum ubi Benedictus</l>
      <l n="47">et ipse suo jacebat in grabato, eisque uno in loco mi-</l>
      <l n="48"></l>
      <l n="49"></l>
      <l n="50"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p372">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">after the ﬂesh beget children of the ﬂesh, must neces-</l>
      <l n="3">sarily seek ﬂeshly and earthly heirs to their ﬂeshly and</l>
      <l n="4">earthly inheritance; but those who by the spiritual seed</l>
      <l n="5">of the Word procreate spiritual sons to God, must of</l>
      <l n="6">like necessity be spiritual in every thing which they do.</l>
      <l n="7">Among their spiritual children, they think him the</l>
      <l n="8">greatest who is possessed of the most abundant grace</l>
      <l n="9">of the Spirit, in the same way as earthly parents con-</l>
      <l n="10">sider their eldest as the principal one of their children,</l>
      <l n="11">and prefer him to the others in dividing out their in-</l>
      <l n="12">heritance.”</l>
      <l n="13"></l>
      <l n="14">Nor must I omit to mention that the venerable Abbot</l>
      <l n="15">Benedict, to lessen the wearisomeness of the night,</l>
      <l n="16">which from his illness he often passed without sleeping,</l>
      <l n="17">would frequently call a reader, and cause him to read</l>
      <l n="18">aloud, as an example for himself, the history of the</l>
      <l n="19">patience of Job, or some other extract from Scripture,</l>
      <l n="20">by which his pains might be alleviated, and his de-</l>
      <l n="21">pressed soul be raised to heavenly things. And because</l>
      <l n="22">he could not get up to pray, nor without difﬁculty lift</l>
      <l n="23">up his voice to the usual extent of daily psalmody, the</l>
      <l n="24">prudent man, in his zeal for religion, at every hour of</l>
      <l n="25">daily or nightly prayer would call to him some of the</l>
      <l n="26">brethren, and making them sing psalms in two compa-</l>
      <l n="27">nies, would himself sing with them, and thus make up</l>
      <l n="28">by their voices for the deﬁciency of his own.</l>
      <l n="29"></l>
      <l n="30">N ow both the abbots saw that they were near death,</l>
      <l n="31">and unﬁt longer to rule the monastery, from increasing</l>
      <l n="32">weakness, which, though tending no doubt to the per-</l>
      <l n="33">fection of Christian purity, was so great, that, when</l>
      <l n="34">they expressed a desire to see one another before they</l>
      <l n="35">died, and Sigfrid was brought in a litter into the room</l>
      <l n="36">where Benedict was lying on his bed, though they were</l>
      <l n="37"></l>
      <l n="38"></l>
      <l n="39"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p373">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">nistrorum manu compositis, caput utriusque in eodem</l>
      <l n="3">cervicali locaretur, lacrimabili spectaculo, nec tantum</l>
      <l n="4">habuere virium, ut propius posita ora ad osculandum</l>
      <l n="5">se alterutrum conjungere possent, sed et hoc fraterno</l>
      <l n="6">compleverunt officio. Inito Benedictus cum eo, cumque</l>
      <l n="7">universis fratribus salubri consilio, accivit abbatem Ceol-</l>
      <l n="8">fridum, quem monasterio beati Pauli Apostoli præfe-</l>
      <l n="9">cerat, virum videlicet sibi non tam carnis necessitudine,</l>
      <l n="10">quam virtutum societate propinquum; et eum utrique</l>
      <l n="11">monasterio, cunctis faventibus atque hoc utillimum ju-</l>
      <l n="12">dicantibus, præposuit Patrem; salubre ratus per omnia</l>
      <l n="13">ad conservandam pacem, unitatem, cöncordiamque loco-</l>
      <l n="14">mm, si unum perpetuo pattern rectoremque tenerent;</l>
      <l n="15">commemorans sæpius Israelitici regni exemplum, quod</l>
      <l n="16">inexterml‘nabile semper exteris nationibus, inviolatum-</l>
      <l n="17">que perduravit, quamdiu unis iisdemque suæ gentis</l>
      <l n="18">regebatur a ducibus; at postquam præcedentium causa</l>
      <l n="19">peccatorum inimico ab invicem est certamine direptum,</l>
      <l n="20">periit paulisper, et a sua concussum soliditate defecit.</l>
      <l n="21">Sed et Evangelicam illam monebat sine intermissione</l>
      <l n="22">recolendam esse sententiam, ‘Quia omne regnum in</l>
      <l n="23">seipso divisum desolabitur.’</l>
      <l n="24"></l>
      <l n="25">GITUR post hæc revolutis men-</l>
      <l n="26">sibus duobus, primo venerabilis ac</l>
      <l n="27">Deo dilectus abbas Sigfridus, per-</l>
      <l n="28">transito igne et aqua tribulationum</l>
      <l n="29">temporalium, inductus est in re-</l>
      <l n="30">frigerium sempiternae quietis; in-</l>
      <l n="31">troiit in domum regni cælestis, in</l>
      <l n="32">holocaustis perpetuae laudationis</l>
      <l n="33">reddens sua vota Domino, quæ sedula labiorum mun-</l>
      <l n="34">dorum distinctione promiserat; ac deinde, adjunctis</l>
      <l n="35">aliis mensibus quatuor, vitiorum victor Benedictus et</l>
      <l n="36">virtutum patrator egregius, victus inﬁrmitate carnis ad</l>
      <l n="37">extrema pervenit. Nox ruit hibernis algida flatibus;</l>
      <l n="38">diem mox sanctam nascitura æternæ felicitatis, sereni-</l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p374">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">placed by the attendants with their heads on the same</l>
      <l n="3">pillow, they had not the power of their own strength to</l>
      <l n="4">kiss one another, but were assisted even in this act of</l>
      <l n="5">fraternal love. After taking counsel with Sigfrid and</l>
      <l n="6">the other brethren, Benedict sent for Ceolfrid, abbot of</l>
      <l n="7">St. Paul’s, dear to him not by relationship of the ﬂesh,</l>
      <l n="8">but by the ties of Christian virtue, and with the consent</l>
      <l n="9">and approbation of all, made him abbot of both monas-</l>
      <l n="10">teries; thinking it expedient in every respect to pre-</l>
      <l n="11">serve peace, unity, and concord between the two, if they</l>
      <l n="12">should have one father and ruler for ever, after the</l>
      <l n="13">example of the kingdom of Israel, which always re-</l>
      <l n="14">mained invincible and inviolate by foreign nations as</l>
      <l n="15">long as it was ruled by one and the same governor of</l>
      <l n="16">its own race; but when for its former sins it was torn</l>
      <l n="17">into opposing factions, it fell by degrees, and, thus</l>
      <l n="18">shorn of its ancient integrity, perished. He reminded</l>
      <l n="19">them also of that evangelical maxim, ever worthy to be</l>
      <l n="20">remembered,—“ A kingdom divided against itself shall</l>
      <l n="21">be laid waste.”</l>
      <l n="22"></l>
      <l n="23">Two months after this, God’s chosen servant, the</l>
      <l n="24">venerable Abbot Sigfrid, having passed through the</l>
      <l n="25">ﬁre and water of temporal tribulation, was carried to</l>
      <l n="26">the resting—place of everlasting repose: he entered the</l>
      <l n="27">mansion of the heavenly kingdom, rendering up whole</l>
      <l n="28">offerings of praise to the Lord which his righteous lips</l>
      <l n="29">had vowed ; and after another space of four months,</l>
      <l n="30">Benedict, who so nobly vanquished sin and wrought</l>
      <l n="31">the deeds of virtue, yielded to the weakness of the ﬂesh,</l>
      <l n="32">and came to his end. Night came on chilled by the</l>
      <l n="33">winter’s blasts, but a day of etemal felicity succeeded, of</l>
      <l n="34"></l>
      <l n="35"></l>
      <l n="36"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p375">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">tatis et lucis. Conveniunt fratres ad ecclesiam, insomnes</l>
      <l n="3">orationibus et psalmis transigunt umbras noctis; et</l>
      <l n="4">paternæ decessionis pondus continua divinæ laudis Amo-</l>
      <l n="5">dulatione solantur. Alii cubiculum, in quo æger, animo</l>
      <l n="6">robustus, egressum mortis et vitæ exspectabat ingres-</l>
      <l n="7">sum, non deserunt. Evangelium tota nocte pro doloris</l>
      <l n="8">levamine, quod et aliis noctibus ﬁeri consueverat, a</l>
      <l n="9">presbytero legitur; Dominici corporis et sanguinis Sa-</l>
      <l n="10">cramentum, hora exitus instante, pro viatico datur; et</l>
      <l n="11">sic anima illa sancta, longis flagellorum felicium excocta</l>
      <l n="12">atque examinata flammis, luteam carnis fornacem de-</l>
      <l n="13">serit, et supernae beatitudinis libera pervolat ad gloriam.</l>
      <l n="14">Cujus egressui victoriosissimo, neque ab immundis spi-</l>
      <l n="15">ritibus aliquatenus impediendo vel retardando, etiam</l>
      <l n="16">psalmus, qui tum pro eo cantabatur, testimonium dat.</l>
      <l n="17">Namque fratres ad ecclesiam principio noctis concur-</l>
      <l n="18">rentes, Psalterium ex ordine decantantes, ad octogesi-</l>
      <l n="19">mum tunc et secundum cantando pervenerant Psalmum,</l>
      <l n="20">qui habet in capite, ‘ Deus, quis similis erit tibi ?’ Cu-</l>
      <l n="21">jus totus hoc resonat textus, quod inimici nominis</l>
      <l n="22">Christi, sive carnales sive spirituales, semper ecclesiam</l>
      <l n="23">Christi, semper animam quamque fidelem disperdere ac</l>
      <l n="24">dissipare conentur; sed e contra ipsi confusi et con-</l>
      <l n="25">turbati sint perituri in seculum, enervaute illos Domino,</l>
      <l n="26">cui non est quisquam similis, qui est solus Altissimus</l>
      <l n="27">super omnem terram. Unde recte dabatur intelligi</l>
      <l n="28">cælitus dispensatum, ut talis diceretur psalmus ea hora,</l>
      <l n="29">qua exiret de corpore anima, cui, juvante Domino, nul-</l>
      <l n="30">lus prævalere posset inimicus. Sextodecimo postquam</l>
      <l n="31">monasterium fundavit anno, quievit in Domino con-</l>
      <l n="32">fessor, secunda die iduum Januariarum, sepultus in</l>
      <l n="33">ecclesia beati Apostoli Petri; ut quem degens in carne</l>
      <l n="34">semper solebat amare, quo pandente januam regni cæ-</l>
      <l n="35"></l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p376">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">serenity and of splendour. The brethren met together at</l>
      <l n="3">the church, and passed the night without sleep in pray-</l>
      <l n="4">ing and singing, consoling their sorrow for their father’s</l>
      <l n="5">departure by one continued outpouring of praise.</l>
      <l n="6">Others clung to the chamber in which the sick man,</l>
      <l n="7">strong in mind, awaited his departure ﬁ'om death and</l>
      <l n="8">his entry into eternal life. A portion of Scripture from</l>
      <l n="9">the Gospels, appointed to be read every evening, was</l>
      <l n="10">recited by a priest during the whole night, to relieve</l>
      <l n="11">their sorrow. The sacrament of our Lord’s ﬂesh and</l>
      <l n="12">blood was given him as a viaticum at the moment of</l>
      <l n="13">his departure; and thus his holy spirit, chastened and</l>
      <l n="14">tried by the lengthened gallings of the lash, operating</l>
      <l n="15">for his own good, abandoned the earthy tenement of</l>
      <l n="16">the ﬂesh, and escaped in freedom to the glory of ever-</l>
      <l n="17">lasting happiness. That his departure was most tri-</l>
      <l n="18">umphant, and neither impeded nor delayed by unclean</l>
      <l n="19">spirits, the psalm which was chanted for him is a proof.</l>
      <l n="20">For the brethren coming together to the church at the</l>
      <l n="21">beginning of the night, sang through the Psalter in</l>
      <l n="22">order, until they came to the 82nd, which begins,</l>
      <l n="23">“ God, who shall be like unto thee ?" The subject of</l>
      <l n="24">the text is this; that the enemies of the Christian name,</l>
      <l n="25">whether carnal or spiritual, are always endeavouring to</l>
      <l n="26">destroy and disperse the church of Christ, and every</l>
      <l n="27">individual soul among the faithful; but that, on the</l>
      <l n="28">other hand, they themselves shall be confounded and</l>
      <l n="29">routed, and shall perish for ever, unnerved before the</l>
      <l n="30">power of the Lord, to whom there is no one equal, for</l>
      <l n="31">He alone is Most Highest over the whole earth. Where-</l>
      <l n="32">fore it was a manifest token of Divine interposition,</l>
      <l n="33">that such a song should be sung at the moment of his</l>
      <l n="34">death, against whom, with God’s aid, no enemy could</l>
      <l n="35">prevail. In the sixteenth year after he built the monas-</l>
      <l n="36">tery, the holy confessor found rest in the Lord, on the</l>
      <l n="37">14th day of January, in the church of St. Peter; and</l>
      <l n="38">thus, as he had loved that holy Apostle in his life, and</l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p377">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">lestis intrabat, ab hujus reliquiis et altari post mortem</l>
      <l n="3">nec corpore longius abesset. Sedecim, ut diximus, annos</l>
      <l n="4">monasterium rexit; primos octo per se sine alterius</l>
      <l n="5">assumtione abbatia, reliquos totidem viris venerabilibus</l>
      <l n="6">et sanctis Easterwino, Sigfrido, et Celfrido abbatis se</l>
      <l n="7">nomine, auctoritate et officio juvantibus; primo quatuor</l>
      <l n="8">annos, secundo tres, tertio unum.</l>
      <l n="9"></l>
      <l n="10">Qui et ipse tertius, id est, Ceolfridus, industrius per</l>
      <l n="11">omnia vir, acutus ingenio, actu impiger, maturus animo,</l>
      <l n="12">religionis zelo fervens, prius, sicut et supra meminimus,</l>
      <l n="13">jubente pariter et juvante Benedicto, monasterium beati</l>
      <l n="14">Pauli Apostoli septem annis, fundavit, perfecit, rexit;</l>
      <l n="15">ac deinde utrique monasterio, vel sicut rectius dicere</l>
      <l n="16">possumus, in duobul locis posito uni monasterio beato-</l>
      <l n="17">rum Apostolorum Petri et Pauli, viginti et octo annos</l>
      <l n="18">solerti regimine præfuit; et cuncta, quæ suus præde-</l>
      <l n="19">cessor egregia virtutum opera cæpit, ipse non segnius</l>
      <l n="20">perficere curavit. Siquidem inter cetera monasterii ne-</l>
      <l n="21">cessaria, quæ longo regendi tempore disponenda com-</l>
      <l n="22">periit, etiam plura fecit oratoria ; altaris et ecclesiæ</l>
      <l n="23">vasa, vel vestimenta omnis generis ampliavit; bibliothe-</l>
      <l n="24">cam utriusque monasterii, quam Benedictus abbas magna</l>
      <l n="25">cæpit instantia, ipse non minori geminavit industria: ita</l>
      <l n="26">ut tres Pandectes novæ translationis ad unum vetustæ</l>
      <l n="27">translationis, quem de Roma attulerat, ipse super ad-</l>
      <l n="28">jungeret; quorum unum senex Romam rediens secum</l>
      <l n="29">inter alia pro munere sumsit, duos utrique monasterio</l>
      <l n="30">reliquit; dato quoque Cosmographorum codice mirandi</l>
      <l n="31">operis, quem Romæ Benedictus emerat, terram octo</l>
      <l n="32"></l>
      <l n="33"></l>
      <l n="34"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p378">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">obtained from him admission into the heavenly kingdom,</l>
      <l n="3">so also after death he rested hard by his relics, and his</l>
      <l n="4">altar, even in the body. He ruled the monastery, as I</l>
      <l n="5">have stated, sixteen years: the ﬁrst eight alone, without</l>
      <l n="6">any assistant abbot; the last eight in conjunction with</l>
      <l n="7">Easterwine, Sigfrid, and Ceolfrid, who enjoyed with him</l>
      <l n="8">the title of abbot, and assisted him in his duties. The</l>
      <l n="9">ﬁrst of these was his colleague four years; the second,</l>
      <l n="10">three; the third, one.</l>
      <l n="11"></l>
      <l n="12">HE third of these, Ceolﬁ'id, was a</l>
      <l n="13"></l>
      <l n="14">,' man of great perseverance, of acute</l>
      <l n="15">, gag intellect,bold in action,experienced</l>
      <l n="16"></l>
      <l n="17">179% in judgment, and zealous in reli-</l>
      <l n="18"></l>
      <l n="19">' ' gion. He ﬁrst of all, as we have</l>
      <l n="20"></l>
      <l n="21">mentioned, with the advice and</l>
      <l n="22"></l>
      <l n="23">«. assistance of Benedict, founded,</l>
      <l n="24"></l>
      <l n="25">completed, and ruled the monas-</l>
      <l n="26"></l>
      <l n="27">tery of St. Paul’s seven years; and, aﬁerwards, ably</l>
      <l n="28">governed, during twenty-eight years, both these monas-</l>
      <l n="29">teries ; or, to speak more correctly, the single monastery</l>
      <l n="30">of St. Peter and St. Paul, in its two separate localities;</l>
      <l n="31">and, whatever works of merit his predecessor had</l>
      <l n="32">begun, he, with no less zeal, took pains to ﬁnish. For,</l>
      <l n="33">among other arrangements which he found it necessary</l>
      <l n="34">to make, during his long government of the monastery,</l>
      <l n="35">he built several oratories; increased the number of</l>
      <l n="36">vessels of the church and altar, and the vestments of</l>
      <l n="37">every kind; and the library of both monasteries, which</l>
      <l n="38">Abbot Benedict had so actively begun, under his equally</l>
      <l n="39">zealous care became doubled in extent. For he added</l>
      <l n="40">three Pandects of a new translation to that of the old</l>
      <l n="41">translation which he had brought from Rome; one of</l>
      <l n="42">them, returning to Rome in his old age, he took with</l>
      <l n="43">him as a giﬁ; the other two he left to the two monas-</l>
      <l n="44">teries. Moreover, for a beautiful volume of the Geo-</l>
      <l n="45"></l>
      <l n="46">graphers which Benedict had bought at Rome, he</l>
      <l n="47"></l>
      <l n="48"></l>
      <l n="49"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p379">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">familiarum juxta fluvium Fresca ab Alfrido rege in</l>
      <l n="3">Scripturis doctissimo, in possessionem monasterii beati</l>
      <l n="4">Pauli Apostoli comparavit; quem comparandi ordinem</l>
      <l n="5">ipse, dum adhuc viveret, Benedictus cum eodem rege</l>
      <l n="6">Alfrido taxaverat, sed prius quam complere potuisset,</l>
      <l n="7">obiit. Verum pro hac terra postmodum, Osredo reg-</l>
      <l n="8">. naute, Ceolfridus, addito pretio digno, terram viginti</l>
      <l n="9"></l>
      <l n="10">familiarum in loco, qui incolarum lingua Ad Villam</l>
      <l n="11">Sambuce vocatur, quia hæc vicinior eidem monasterio</l>
      <l n="12">videbatur, accepit. Missis Romam monachis tempore</l>
      <l n="13">beatæ recordationis Sergii papæ, privilegium ab eo pro</l>
      <l n="14">tuitione sui monasterii instar illius, quod Agatho papa</l>
      <l n="15">Benedicto dederat, accepit; quod Britannias perlatum,</l>
      <l n="16">et coram synodo patefactum, præsentium episcoporum</l>
      <l n="17">simul et magnifici regis Alfridi subscriptione conﬁr-</l>
      <l n="18">matum est, quomodo etiam prius illud sui temporis</l>
      <l n="19">regem et episcopos in synodo publice confirmasse non</l>
      <l n="20">latet. Temporibus illius tradens se monasterio beati</l>
      <l n="21"></l>
      <l n="22">Petri Apostoli, quod regebat veteranus ac religiosus, et</l>
      <l n="23">in omni tam seculari quam Scripturarum scientia eru-</l>
      <l n="24">ditus Christi famulus Witmer, terram decem familia-</l>
      <l n="25">rum, quam ab Alfrido rege in possessionem acceperat,</l>
      <l n="26">in loco villæ, quæ Daldun nuncupatur, eidem monasterio</l>
      <l n="27">perpetuæ possessionis jure donavit.</l>
      <l n="28"></l>
      <l n="29">At ubi Ceolfridus post multam regularis observantiae</l>
      <l n="30">disciplinam, quam sibi ipsi pariter ac suis pater Bene-</l>
      <l n="31">dictus providus ex priorum auctoritate contribuit;</l>
      <l n="32">post incomparabilem orandi psallendique solertiam, qua</l>
      <l n="33">ipse quotidianus exerceri non desiit ; post mirabilem et</l>
      <l n="34">coercendi improbos fervorem, et modestiam consolandi</l>
      <l n="35">infirmos; post insolitam rectoribus et escæ potusque</l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37"></l>
      <l n="38"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p380">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">received from king Alfrid, who was well skilled in</l>
      <l n="3">Holy Scripture, in exchange, a grant of land of eight</l>
      <l n="4">hides, near the river Fresca, for the monastery of St.</l>
      <l n="5">Paul’s. Benedict had arranged this purchase with the</l>
      <l n="6">same King Alfrid, before his death, but died before he</l>
      <l n="7">could complete it. Instead of this land, Ceolfrid, in</l>
      <l n="8">the reign of Osred, paid an additional price, and received</l>
      <l n="9">&amp; territory of twenty hides, in the village called by the</l>
      <l n="10">natives Sambuce, and situated much nearer to the</l>
      <l n="11">monastery. In the time of Pope Sefgius, of blessed</l>
      <l n="12">memory, some monks were sent to Rome, who procured</l>
      <l n="13">from him a privilege for the protection of their monas-</l>
      <l n="14">tery, similar to that which Pope Agatha had given to</l>
      <l n="15">Benedict. This was brought back to Britain, and,</l>
      <l n="16">being exhibited before a synod, was conﬁrmed by the</l>
      <l n="17">signatures of the bishops who were present, and their A</l>
      <l n="18">muniﬁcent King Alfrid, just as the former privilege</l>
      <l n="19">was conﬁrmed publicly by the king and bishops of the</l>
      <l n="20"></l>
      <l n="21">time. Zealous for the welfare of St. Peter’s monastery,</l>
      <l n="22">at that time under the government of the reverend and</l>
      <l n="23">religious servant of Christ, Witmer, whose acquaintance</l>
      <l n="24">with every kind of learning, both sacred and profane,</l>
      <l n="25">was equally extensive, he made a gift of it for ever of a</l>
      <l n="26">portion of land of ten hides, which he had received</l>
      <l n="27">from King Alfrid, in the village called Daldun.</l>
      <l n="28"></l>
      <l n="29">UT Ceolfrid having now practised</l>
      <l n="30"></l>
      <l n="31">a long course of regular discipline,</l>
      <l n="32"></l>
      <l n="33">which the prudent father Benedict</l>
      <l n="34"></l>
      <l n="35">had laid down for himself and his</l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37">brethren on the authority of the</l>
      <l n="38"></l>
      <l n="39">elders; and having shown the most</l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41">‘ incomparable skill both in praying</l>
      <l n="42"></l>
      <l n="43">and chanting, in which he daily</l>
      <l n="44"></l>
      <l n="45">exercised himself, together with the most wonderful</l>
      <l n="46">energy in punishing the wicked, and modesty in con-</l>
      <l n="47">soling the weak; having also observed such abstinence</l>
      <l n="48"></l>
      <l n="49"></l>
      <l n="50"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p381">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">parcitatem, et habitus vilitatem; vidit se jam senior et</l>
      <l n="3">plenus dierum non ultra posse subditis, ob impedimen-</l>
      <l n="4">tum supremæ ætatis, debitam spiritualis exercitii, vel</l>
      <l n="5">docendo vel vivendo, præfigere formam; multa diu</l>
      <l n="6">secum mente versans, utilius decrevit, dato fratribus</l>
      <l n="7">præcepto, ut juxta sui statuta privilegii, juxtaque regu-</l>
      <l n="8">lam sancti abbatis Benedicti, de suis sibi ipsi patrem,</l>
      <l n="9">qui aptior esset, eligerent ; ipse beatorum Apostolorum,</l>
      <l n="10">ubi juvenis cum Benedicto fuerat, Romæ loca sancta</l>
      <l n="11">repeteret: quafenus et ipse ante mortem aliquamdiu</l>
      <l n="12">seculi curis absolutus, liberius sibimet secreta quiete</l>
      <l n="13">vacaret; et illi, sumto abbate juniore, perfectius</l>
      <l n="14">juxta ætatem magistri, quæ vitæ regularis essent insti-</l>
      <l n="15">tuta, servarent.</l>
      <l n="16"></l>
      <l n="17">« BNITENTIBUS licet primo om-</l>
      <l n="18"></l>
      <l n="19">nibus, et in lacrimas singultusque</l>
      <l n="20"></l>
      <l n="21">genua cum obsecratione crebra</l>
      <l n="22"></l>
      <l n="23">flectentibus, factum est quod voluit.</l>
      <l n="24"></l>
      <l n="25">, Tantaque erat proﬁciscendi cupido,</l>
      <l n="26"></l>
      <l n="27">ut tertia die, ex quo ﬁ'atribus se-</l>
      <l n="28"></l>
      <l n="29">“m cretum sui propositi aperuit, iter</l>
      <l n="30"></l>
      <l n="31">arriperet. Timebat enim, quod</l>
      <l n="32"></l>
      <l n="33">evenit, ue priusquam Romam pervenire posset, obiret;</l>
      <l n="34">simul devitans, ne ab amicis sive viris principalibus,</l>
      <l n="35">quibus cunctis erat honorabilis, ejus coepta retardarentur,</l>
      <l n="36">et ne pecunia daretur illi a quibusdam, quibus retri-</l>
      <l n="37">buere pro tempore nequiret; hanc habens semper con-</l>
      <l n="38">suetudinem, ut si quis ei aliquid muneris offerret, hoc</l>
      <l n="39">illi vel statim, vel post intervallum competens, non</l>
      <l n="40">minore gratia rependeret. Cantata ergo primo mane</l>
      <l n="41">missa in ecclesia beatæ Dei Genetricis semperque vir-</l>
      <l n="42">ginis Mariæ, et in ecclesia Apostoli Petri, pridie nonas</l>
      <l n="43"></l>
      <l n="44"></l>
      <l n="45"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p382">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">in meat and drink, and such humility in dress, as are</l>
      <l n="3">uncommon among rulers ; saw himself now old and full</l>
      <l n="4">of days, and unﬁt any longer, from his extreme age, to</l>
      <l n="5">prescribe to his brethren the proper forms of spiritual</l>
      <l n="6">exercise by his life and doctrine. Having, therefore,</l>
      <l n="7">deliberated long within himself, he judged it expedient,</l>
      <l n="8">having ﬁrst impressed on the brethren the observance</l>
      <l n="9">of the rules which St. Benedict had given them, and</l>
      <l n="10">thereby to choose for themselves a more efﬁcient abbot</l>
      <l n="11">out of their own number, to depart, himself, to Rome,</l>
      <l n="12">where he had been in his youth with the holy Bene-</l>
      <l n="13">dict ; that not only he might for a time be free from all</l>
      <l n="14">worldly cares before his death, and so have leisure and</l>
      <l n="15">quiet for reﬂection, but that they also, having chosen a</l>
      <l n="16">younger abbot, might naturally, in consequence thereof,</l>
      <l n="17">observe more accurately the rules of monastic disci-</l>
      <l n="18"></l>
      <l n="19">..ll' ID cqlx'ﬁ</l>
      <l n="20">s: him on their knees and with many</l>
      <l n="21"></l>
      <l n="22">: tears, but their solicitations were</l>
      <l n="23"></l>
      <l n="24">y' to no purpose. Such was his</l>
      <l n="25"></l>
      <l n="26">' eagemess to depart, that on the</l>
      <l n="27"></l>
      <l n="28">‘x * third day after he had disclosed</l>
      <l n="29"></l>
      <l n="30">his design to the brethren, he set</l>
      <l n="31"></l>
      <l n="32">out upon his journey. For he</l>
      <l n="33"></l>
      <l n="34">feared, what actually came to pass, that he might die</l>
      <l n="35">before he reached Rome; and he was also anxious that</l>
      <l n="36">neither his friends nor the nobility, who all honoured</l>
      <l n="37">him, should delay his departure, or give him money</l>
      <l n="38">which he would not have time to repay ; for with him</l>
      <l n="39">it was an invariable rule, if any one made him a pre-</l>
      <l n="40">sent, to show equal grace by returning it, either at once</l>
      <l n="41">or within a suitable space of time. Early in the mom-</l>
      <l n="42">ing, therefore, of Wednesday, the 4th of May, the mass</l>
      <l n="43">was sung in the church of the Mother of God, the im-</l>
      <l n="44">maculate Virgin Mary, and in the church of the Apostle</l>
      <l n="45"></l>
      <l n="46">,"! T ﬁrst all opposed, and entreated</l>
      <l n="47"></l>
      <l n="48"></l>
      <l n="49"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p383">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">Junias, quinta feria, et communicantibus qui aderant,</l>
      <l n="3">continuo præparatur ad eundum. Conveniunt omnes</l>
      <l n="4">in ecclesiam beati" Petri, ipse thure inbenso et dicta</l>
      <l n="5">oratione ad altare, pacem dat omnibus, stans in gra-</l>
      <l n="6">dibus, thuribulum habens in manu. Hinc, ﬂetibus</l>
      <l n="7">universorum inter litanias resonantibus, exeunt; beati</l>
      <l n="8">Laurentii martyris oratorium, quod in dormitorio fra-</l>
      <l n="9">trum erat obvium, intrant; vale dicens ultimum, de</l>
      <l n="10">conservanda invicem dilectione, et delinquentibus juxta</l>
      <l n="11">Evangelii regulam corripiendis, admonet; omnibus, si</l>
      <l n="12">quid forte deliquissent, gratiam suæ remissionis et pla-</l>
      <l n="13">cationis offert; omnes pro se orare, sibi placatos exsis-</l>
      <l n="14">tere, si sint quos durius justo redarguisset, obsecrat.</l>
      <l n="15">Veniunt ad littus; rursum osculo pacis inter lacrimas</l>
      <l n="16">omnes dato genua flectunt; dat orationem, ascendit</l>
      <l n="17">navem cum comitibus. Ascendunt et diacones ecclesiæ</l>
      <l n="18">cereas ardentes et crucem ferentes auream, transit</l>
      <l n="19">flumen, adorat crucem, ascendit equum et abiit, relictis</l>
      <l n="20">in monasteriis suis fratribus numero ferme sexcentis.</l>
      <l n="21"></l>
      <l n="22">Illo autem abeunte cum sociis, redeunt ad ecclesiam</l>
      <l n="23">fratres, se ac sua Domino fletibus et oratione commen-</l>
      <l n="24">dant: et post non grande intervallum completa horæ</l>
      <l n="25">tertiæ psalmodia, rursum conveniunt omnes ; quid</l>
      <l n="26">agendum sit consulunt; orando, psallendo, et jejunando</l>
      <l n="27">Patrem citius a Deo quærendum decernunt ; monachis</l>
      <l n="28">beati Pauli, fratribus videlicet suis, per eorum quosdam</l>
      <l n="29">qui aderant, necnon et suorum aliquos, quid decreverint,</l>
      <l n="30">pandunt. Assentiunt et illi, fit utrorumque animus</l>
      <l n="31"></l>
      <l n="32"></l>
      <l n="33"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p384">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">Peter; and those who were present communicating</l>
      <l n="3">with him, he prepared for his departure. All of them</l>
      <l n="4">assembled in St. Peter’s church; and-when he had</l>
      <l n="5">lighted the frankincense, and addressed a prayer at the</l>
      <l n="6">altar, he gave his blessing to all, standing on the steps</l>
      <l n="7">and holding the censer in his hand. Amid the prayers</l>
      <l n="8">of the Litany, the cry of sorrow resounded from all as</l>
      <l n="9">they went out of the church: they entered the oratory</l>
      <l n="10">of St. Laurence the martyr, which was in the dormitory</l>
      <l n="11">of the brethren over-against them. Whilst giving them</l>
      <l n="12">his last farewell, he admonished them to preserve love</l>
      <l n="13">towards one another, and to correct, according to the</l>
      <l n="14">Gospel rule, those who did amiss: he forgave all of</l>
      <l n="15">them whatever wrong they might have done him; and</l>
      <l n="16">entreated them all to pray for him, and to be reconciled</l>
      <l n="17">to him, if he had ever reprimanded them too harshly.</l>
      <l n="18">They went down to the shore, and there, amid tears and</l>
      <l n="19">lamentations, he gave them the kiss of peace, as they</l>
      <l n="20">knelt upon their knees; and when he had oﬂ'ered up a</l>
      <l n="21">prayer he went on board the vessel with his compa-</l>
      <l n="22">nions. The deacons of the Church went on board with</l>
      <l n="23">him, carrying lighted tapers and a golden cruciﬁx.</l>
      <l n="24">Having crossed the river, he kissed the cross, mounted</l>
      <l n="25">his horse, and departed, leaving in both his monasteries</l>
      <l n="26">about six hundred brethren.</l>
      <l n="27"></l>
      <l n="28">When he was gone, the brethren returned to the</l>
      <l n="29">church, and with much weeping and prayer commended</l>
      <l n="30">themselves and theirs to the protection of the Lord.</l>
      <l n="31">After a short interval, having ended the nine o’clock</l>
      <l n="32">psalm, they again assembled, and deliberated what was</l>
      <l n="33">to be done. At length they resolved, with prayer,</l>
      <l n="34">hymns, and fasting, to seek of the Lord a new abbot</l>
      <l n="35">as soon as possible. This resolution they communi-</l>
      <l n="36">cated to their brethren of St. Paul’s, by some of that</l>
      <l n="37">monastery who were present, and also by some of their</l>
      <l n="38">own people. They immediately gave their consent, and</l>
      <l n="39">both monasteries showing the same spirit, they all toge-</l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41">c c</l>
      <l n="42"></l>
      <l n="43"></l>
      <l n="44"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p385">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">upus, omnium corda sursum, omnium levantur voces ad</l>
      <l n="3">Dominum. Tandem die tertia, veniente Dominico die</l>
      <l n="4">Pentecostes, conveniunt omnes qui erant in monasterio</l>
      <l n="5">beati Petri in concilium, adsunt et de monasterio beati</l>
      <l n="6">Pauli seniorum non pauci. Fit una concordia, eadem</l>
      <l n="7">utrorumque sententia. Eligitur itaque abbas Huet-</l>
      <l n="8">bertus, qui a primis pueritiæ temporibus eodem in</l>
      <l n="9">monasterio non solum regularis observantia disciplinæ</l>
      <l n="10">institutus, sed et scribendi, cantandi, legendi ac docendi</l>
      <l n="11">fuerat non parva exercitatus industria. Romam quoque</l>
      <l n="12">temporibus beatæ memoriæ Sergii papæ accurrens, et</l>
      <l n="13">non parvo ibidem temporis spatio demoratus, quæcum-</l>
      <l n="14">que sibi necessaria judicabat, didicit, descripsit, retulit;</l>
      <l n="15">insuper et duodecim ante hæc annos presbyterii est</l>
      <l n="16">functus oﬁcio. Hic igitur electus abbas ab omnibus</l>
      <l n="17">utriusque præfati monasterii fratribus, statim assumtis</l>
      <l n="18">secum aliquibus fratrum, venit ad abbatem Ceolfridum,</l>
      <l n="19">cursum navis, qua oceanum transiret, exspectantem;</l>
      <l n="20">quem elegerunt abbatem nunciant; ‘Deo gratias,, re-</l>
      <l n="21">spondit, electionem confirmat, et commendatoriam ab</l>
      <l n="22">eo epistolam apostolico papæ Gregorio deferendam sus-</l>
      <l n="23">cepit; cujus, memoriæ causa, putavimus etiam in hoc</l>
      <l n="24">opere versus aliquot esse ponendos.</l>
      <l n="25"></l>
      <l n="26">‘ Domino in Domino dominorum dilectissime, terque</l>
      <l n="27">beatissimo papæ Gregorio, Huetbertus humilis servus</l>
      <l n="28">vester, abbas cænobii beatissimi Apostolorum principis</l>
      <l n="29">Petri in Saxonia, perpetuam in Domino salutem.</l>
      <l n="30"></l>
      <l n="31">'Gratias agere non cesso dispensationi superni exa-</l>
      <l n="32">minis, una cum sanctis fratribus, qui mecum in-his locis</l>
      <l n="33">ad inveniendam requiem animabus suis suavissimum</l>
      <l n="34">Christi jugum portare desiderant, quod te nostris tem-</l>
      <l n="35">poribus tam gloriﬁcum electionis vas regimini totius</l>
      <l n="36">ecclesiæ praeficere dignatus est, quatenus per hoc quo</l>
      <l n="37">ipse impleris lumen veritatis et fidei, etiam minores</l>
      <l n="38">quosque affatim jubare suæ pietatis aspergeret. Com-</l>
      <l n="39">mendamus autem tuæ sanctæ benignitati, dilectissime</l>
      <l n="40">in Christo pater et domine, venerabiles patris nostri</l>
      <l n="41"></l>
      <l n="42"></l>
      <l n="43"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p386">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">ther lifted up their hearts and voices to the Lord. At</l>
      <l n="3">length, on the third day, which was Easter Sunday, an</l>
      <l n="4">assembly was held, consisting of all the brethren of St.</l>
      <l n="5">Peter’s and several of the elder monks from the monas-</l>
      <l n="6">tery of St. Paul’s. The greatest concord prevailed, and</l>
      <l n="7">the same sentiments were expressed by both. They</l>
      <l n="8">elected for their new abbot, Huetbert, who from his</l>
      <l n="9">boyhood had not only been bred up in the regular dis-</l>
      <l n="10">cipline of the monastery, but had acquired much expe-</l>
      <l n="11">rience in the various duties of writing, chanting, read-</l>
      <l n="12">ing, and teaching. He had been at Rome in the time</l>
      <l n="13">of Pope Sergius, of blessed memory, and had there</l>
      <l n="14">learnt and copied every thing which he thought useful</l>
      <l n="15">or worthy to be brought away. He had also been</l>
      <l n="16">twelve years in priest’s orders. He was now made</l>
      <l n="17">abbot; and immediately went with some of the bre-</l>
      <l n="18">thren to Ceolfrid, who was waiting for a ship in which</l>
      <l n="19">to cross the ocean. They told him what they had done,</l>
      <l n="20"></l>
      <l n="21">for which he gave thanks to God, in approbation of</l>
      <l n="22">their choice, and received from his successor a letter of</l>
      <l n="23">recommendation to Pope Gregory, of which I have pre-</l>
      <l n="24">served the few passages which follow.</l>
      <l n="25"></l>
      <l n="26">“ To our most beloved lord in the Lord of lords,</l>
      <l n="27">and thrice blessed Pope Gregory, Huetbert, his most.</l>
      <l n="28">humble servant, abbot of the monastery of the holiest</l>
      <l n="29">of the Apostles, St. Peter, in Saxony, Health for ever</l>
      <l n="30">in the Lord! I do not cease to give thanks to the dis-</l>
      <l n="31">pensation of Divine wisdom, as do also all the holy</l>
      <l n="32">brethren, who in these parts are seeking with me to</l>
      <l n="33">bear the pleasant yoke of Christ, that they may ﬁnd</l>
      <l n="34">rest to their souls, that God has condescended to ap-</l>
      <l n="35">point so glorious a vessel of election tonile the Church</l>
      <l n="36">in these our times; and by means of the light of truth</l>
      <l n="37">and faith with which you are full, to scatter the beams</l>
      <l n="38">of his love on all your inferiors also. We recommend</l>
      <l n="39">to your holy clemency, most beloved father and lord in</l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41">c c 2</l>
      <l n="42"></l>
      <l n="43"></l>
      <l n="44"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p387">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">dilectissimi canos, Ceolfridi videlicet abbatis, ac nutri-</l>
      <l n="3">toris tutorisque nostræ spiritualis m monastica quiete</l>
      <l n="4">libertatis et pacis. Et primum quidem gratias agimus</l>
      <l n="5">sanctæ et individuae Trinitati, quod ipse, etsi non sine</l>
      <l n="6">maximo nostro dolore, gemitu, luctu, ac prosecutione</l>
      <l n="7">lacrimarum a nobis abiit, ad suæ tamen diu desideratæ</l>
      <l n="8">quietis gaudia sancta pervenit; dum ea, quæ juvenem</l>
      <l n="9">se adiisse, vidisse atque adorasse semper recordans</l>
      <l n="10">exsultabat, etiam senio defessus beatorum Apostolorum</l>
      <l n="11">devotus limina repetiit. Et post longos amplius qua-</l>
      <l n="12">draginta annorum labores curasque continuas, quibus</l>
      <l n="13">monasteriis regendis abbatis jure præfuit, incomparabili</l>
      <l n="14">virtutis amore, quasi nuper ad conversationem vitæ</l>
      <l n="15">cælestis accitus, ultima confectus ætate, et prope jam</l>
      <l n="16">moriturus, mrsus incipit peregrinari pro Christo, quo</l>
      <l n="17">liberius prisca. sollicitudinum secularium spineta, camino</l>
      <l n="18">spirituali fervens compunctionis ignis absumat.</l>
      <l n="19"></l>
      <l n="20">‘Deinde etiam vestræ paternitati supplicamus, ut</l>
      <l n="21">quod nos facere non meruimus, vos erga illum ultimæ</l>
      <l n="22">pietatis seduli munum expleatis ; pro certo scientes,</l>
      <l n="23">quia etsi Vos corpus habetis ipsius, et nos tamen et vos</l>
      <l n="24">Deo devotum ejus spiritum sive in corpore manentem,</l>
      <l n="25">seu cameis vinculis absolutum, magnum pro nostris</l>
      <l n="26">excessibus apud supernam pietatem intercessorem ha-</l>
      <l n="27">bemus et patronum., Et cetera, quæ epistolæ sequentia</l>
      <l n="28">continent.</l>
      <l n="29"></l>
      <l n="30">Reverso autem domum Huetberto, advocatur episco-</l>
      <l n="31">pus Acca, et solita illum in abbatis officium benedic-</l>
      <l n="32">tione conﬁrmat. Qui inter innumera monasterii jura,</l>
      <l n="33">quæ juvenili sagax solertia recuperabat, hoc in primis</l>
      <l n="34">omnibus delectabile et gratiﬁcum fecit; sustulit ossa</l>
      <l n="35">Easterwini abbatis, quae in porticu ingressus ecclesiæ</l>
      <l n="36">beati Apostoli Petri erant posita; necnon et ossa Sig-</l>
      <l n="37">fridi abbatis ac magistri quondam sui, quæ foris Sacra-</l>
      <l n="38">rium ad meridiem fuerant condita, et utraque in una</l>
      <l n="39">theca, sed medio pariete divisa, recludens, intus 'in</l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41"></l>
      <l n="42"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p388">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">Christ, the grey hairs of our venerable and beloved</l>
      <l n="3">father Abbot Ceolfrid, the supporter and defender of</l>
      <l n="4">our spiritual liberty and peace in this monastic retire-</l>
      <l n="5">ment; and, in the ﬁrst place, we give thanks to the</l>
      <l n="6">holy and undivided Trinity, for that, although he hath</l>
      <l n="7">caused us much sorrow, lamentation, and tears, by his</l>
      <l n="8">departure, he hath nevertheless arrived at the enjoyment</l>
      <l n="9">of that rest which he long desired; whilst he was in his</l>
      <l n="10">old age devoutly returning to that threshold of the holy</l>
      <l n="11">Apostles, which he exultingly boasted, that when a</l>
      <l n="12">youth he had visited, seen, and worshipped. After</l>
      <l n="13">more than forty years of care and toil, during his</l>
      <l n="14">government of the monasteries, by his wonderful love</l>
      <l n="15">of virtue, as if recently incited to conversation with the</l>
      <l n="16">heavenly life, though worn out with extreme old age,</l>
      <l n="17">and already almost at the gates of death, he a second</l>
      <l n="18">time undertakes to travel in the cause of Christ, that</l>
      <l n="19">the thorns of his former secular anxieties may be con-</l>
      <l n="20">sumed by the ﬁre of zeal blazing forth from that</l>
      <l n="21">spiritual furnace. We next entreat your fatherly love,</l>
      <l n="22">that, though we have not merited to do this, you will</l>
      <l n="23">carefully fulﬁl towards him the last oﬂices; knowing</l>
      <l n="24">for certain, that though you may possess his body, yet</l>
      <l n="25">both we and you shall have in his devout spirit, whether</l>
      <l n="26">in the body or out of the body, a mighty intercessor</l>
      <l n="27">and protector over our own last moments, at the throne</l>
      <l n="28">of grace.” And so on through the rest of the letter.</l>
      <l n="29">When Huetbert had returned to the monastery,</l>
      <l n="30">Bishop Acca was sent for to conﬁrm the election with</l>
      <l n="31">his blessing. Afterwards, by his youthful zeal and</l>
      <l n="32">wisdom, he gained many privileges for the monastery ;</l>
      <l n="33">and, amongst others, one which gave great delight to</l>
      <l n="34">all, he took up the bones of Abbot Easterwine, which</l>
      <l n="35">lay in the entrance porch of St. Peter’s, and also the</l>
      <l n="36">bones of his old preceptor, Abbot Sigfrid, which had</l>
      <l n="37">been buried outside the Sacrarium towards the south,</l>
      <l n="38">and placing both together in one chest, but separated</l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p389">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">eadem ecclesia juxta corpus beati patris Benedicti com-</l>
      <l n="3">posuit. Fecit autem hæc die natalis Sigfridi, id est,</l>
      <l n="4">undecimo kalendarum Septembrium, quo etiam die</l>
      <l n="5">mira Dei providentia contigit, ut venerandus Christi</l>
      <l n="6">famulus Witmer, cujus supra meminimus, excederet, et</l>
      <l n="7">in loco ubi prædicti abbates prius sepulti fuerant, ipse,</l>
      <l n="8">qui eorum imitator fuerat, conderetur.</l>
      <l n="9"></l>
      <l n="10">Christi vero famulus Ceolfridus, ut supra dictum est,</l>
      <l n="11">ad limina beatorum apostolorum tendens, prius quam</l>
      <l n="12">illo pervenisset, tactus infirmitate diem clausit ultimum.</l>
      <l n="13">Perveniens namque Lingonas circa horam diei tertiam,</l>
      <l n="14">decima ipsius diei hora migravit ad Dominum, et cras-</l>
      <l n="15">tino in ecclesia beatorum geminorum martyrum hono-</l>
      <l n="16">riﬁce sepultus est, non solum Anglis genere, qui plus</l>
      <l n="17">quam octoginta numero in ejus fuerant comitatu, sed et</l>
      <l n="18">illius loci accolis, pro retardato tam reverendi senis</l>
      <l n="19">desiderio, in lacrimas luctusque solutis. Neque enim</l>
      <l n="20">facile quisquam lacrimas tenere potuit, videns comites</l>
      <l n="21">ipsius partim, patre amisso, cæptum iter agere; partim,</l>
      <l n="22">mutata intentione, qua Romam ire desiderarant, domum</l>
      <l n="23">magis qua hunc sepultum nunciarent reverti; partim ad</l>
      <l n="24">tumbam defuncti inter eos, quorum nec linguam nove-</l>
      <l n="25">rant, pro inextinguibili patris affectu residere.</l>
      <l n="26"></l>
      <l n="27">RAT autem quando obiit annorum</l>
      <l n="28"></l>
      <l n="29">septuaginta quatuor, presbyterii</l>
      <l n="30"></l>
      <l n="31">gradu functus annis quadraginta.</l>
      <l n="32"></l>
      <l n="33">* septem, abbatis officium ministrans</l>
      <l n="34"></l>
      <l n="35">annis triginta quinque, vel potius</l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37">annis quadraginta tribus, quia sci-</l>
      <l n="38"></l>
      <l n="39">licet a primo tempore quo Bene-</l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41">dictus in honore beatissimi Aposto-</l>
      <l n="42"></l>
      <l n="43">lorum principis suum cæpit condere monasterium, ipse</l>
      <l n="44">illi comes individuus, cooperator et doctor regularis et</l>
      <l n="45"></l>
      <l n="46"></l>
      <l n="47"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p390">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">by a partition, laid them within the church near the</l>
      <l n="3">body of St. Benedict. He did this on Sigfrid’s birth-</l>
      <l n="4">day, the 23rd of August ; and on the same day Divine</l>
      <l n="5">Providence so ordered that Christ’s venerable servant</l>
      <l n="6">Witmer, whom we have already mentioned, departed</l>
      <l n="7">this life, and was buried in the same place as the afore-</l>
      <l n="8">said abbots, whose life he had imitated.</l>
      <l n="9"></l>
      <l n="10">«- UT Christ’s servant Ceolfrid, as</l>
      <l n="11">has been said, died on his way to</l>
      <l n="12"></l>
      <l n="13">of old age and weakness. For he</l>
      <l n="14">reached the Lingones about nine</l>
      <l n="15"></l>
      <l n="16">the next day' m the church of the</l>
      <l n="17">three twin martyrs, much to the sorrow, not only of the</l>
      <l n="18">English who were in his train, to the number of eighty,</l>
      <l n="19">but also of the neighbouring inhabitants, who were dis-</l>
      <l n="20">solved in tears at the loss of the reverend father. For</l>
      <l n="21">it was almost impossible to avoid weeping to see part of</l>
      <l n="22">his company continuing their journey without the holy</l>
      <l n="23">father, whilst others, abandoning their ﬁrst intentions,</l>
      <l n="24">returned home to relate his death and burial ; and</l>
      <l n="25">others, again, lingered in sorrow at the tomb of the de-</l>
      <l n="26">ceased among strangers speaking an unknown tongue.</l>
      <l n="27"></l>
      <l n="28">EOLFRID was seventy—four years</l>
      <l n="29"></l>
      <l n="30">old when he died: forty-seven years</l>
      <l n="31"></l>
      <l n="32">he had been in priest’s orders,</l>
      <l n="33"></l>
      <l n="34">during tbirty-ﬁve of which he had</l>
      <l n="35"></l>
      <l n="36">been abbot; or, to speak more</l>
      <l n="37"></l>
      <l n="38">. correctly, forty-three,——for, from</l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40">": the time when Benedict began to</l>
      <l n="41"></l>
      <l n="42">build his monastery in honour of</l>
      <l n="43"></l>
      <l n="44">the holiest of the Apostles, Ceolfrid had been his only</l>
      <l n="45">companion, coadjutor, and teacher of the monastic rules.</l>
      <l n="46"></l>
      <l n="47"></l>
      <l n="48"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p391">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">monasticæ institutionis aderat. Cui ne prisci morem</l>
      <l n="3">rigoris vel ætatis, vel infirmitatis, vel itineris unquam</l>
      <l n="4">minueret occasio; ex die quo de monasterio suo pro-</l>
      <l n="5">fectus abiit usque ad diem quo defunctus est, id est, a.</l>
      <l n="6">pridie nonas Junias usque ad septimum kalendarum</l>
      <l n="7">Octobrium diem, per dies centum quatuordecim, ex-</l>
      <l n="8">ceptis canonicis orationum horis, quotidie bis psalterium</l>
      <l n="9">ex ordine decantare curavit; etiam cum ad hoc per in-</l>
      <l n="10">ﬁrmitatem deveniret, ut equitare non valens feretro</l>
      <l n="11">caballario veheretur, quotidie missa cantata salutaris</l>
      <l n="12">hostiæ Deo munus offerret, excepto uno, quo oceanum</l>
      <l n="13">navigabat, et tribus ante exitum diebus.</l>
      <l n="14"></l>
      <l n="15">, xx,; NBIIT autem septimo kalendarum</l>
      <l n="16"></l>
      <l n="17">' 7635:) Octobrium die, anno ab incarna-</l>
      <l n="18"></l>
      <l n="19">tione Domini septingentesimo sex-</l>
      <l n="20"></l>
      <l n="21">todecimo, feria sexta, post horam</l>
      <l n="22"></l>
      <l n="23">nonam, in pratis memoratæ civi-</l>
      <l n="24"></l>
      <l n="25">tatis; sepultus in "crastinum ad</l>
      <l n="26"></l>
      <l n="27">' austrum ejusdem civitatis milliario</l>
      <l n="28"></l>
      <l n="29">primo in monasterio Geminorum,</l>
      <l n="30"></l>
      <l n="31">astante ac psalmos resonante exercitu non parvo tam</l>
      <l n="32"></l>
      <l n="33">Anglorum, qui cum eo advenerant, quam monasterii</l>
      <l n="34"></l>
      <l n="35">ejusdem vel civitatis incolarum. Sunt autem Gemini</l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37">martyres, in quorum monasterio et ecclesia conditus</l>
      <l n="38"></l>
      <l n="39">est, Speusippus, Eleusippus, Meleusippus, qui uno</l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41">partu matris editi, eadem ecclesiæ ﬁde renati, simul</l>
      <l n="42"></l>
      <l n="43">cum avia sua Leonella, dignam loco illi sui martyrii</l>
      <l n="44"></l>
      <l n="45">reliquere memoriam, qui piam etiam nobis indignis et</l>
      <l n="46"></l>
      <l n="47">nostro parenti opem suæ intercessionis et protectionis</l>
      <l n="48">impendant.</l>
      <l n="49"></l>
      <l n="50"></l>
      <l n="51"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p392">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">He never relaxed the rigour of ancient discipline from</l>
      <l n="3">any occasions of old age, illness, or travel; for, from</l>
      <l n="4">the day of his departure till the day of his death, i.e.</l>
      <l n="5">from the 4th of June till the 25th of September, a</l>
      <l n="6">space of one hundred and fourteen days, besides the</l>
      <l n="7">canonical hours of pmyer, he never omitted to go twice</l>
      <l n="8">daily through the Psalter in order; and even when he</l>
      <l n="9">became so weak that he could not ride on horseback,</l>
      <l n="10">and was obliged to be carried in a horse-litter, the holy</l>
      <l n="11">ceremony of the mass was offered up every day, except</l>
      <l n="12">one which he passed at sea, and the three days imme-</l>
      <l n="13">diately before his death.</l>
      <l n="14"></l>
      <l n="15">E died on Friday, the 25th of Sep-</l>
      <l n="16"></l>
      <l n="17">‘ ($9 tember, in the year of our Lord</l>
      <l n="18"></l>
      <l n="19">" ' '— 716, between three and four o’clock,</l>
      <l n="20"></l>
      <l n="21">: in the ﬁelds of the city before men-</l>
      <l n="22"></l>
      <l n="23">tioned, and was buried the next</l>
      <l n="24"></l>
      <l n="25">day near the ﬁrst milestone on the</l>
      <l n="26"></l>
      <l n="27">&amp; south side of the city, in the mo-</l>
      <l n="28"></l>
      <l n="29">nastery of the Twins, followed by a</l>
      <l n="30"></l>
      <l n="31">large number of his English attendants, and the inha-</l>
      <l n="32"></l>
      <l n="33">bitants of the city and monastery. The names of these</l>
      <l n="34"></l>
      <l n="35">twin martyrs are Speusippus, Eleusippus, and Melen-</l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37">sippus. They were born at one birth, and born again</l>
      <l n="38"></l>
      <l n="39">by baptism at the same time: together with their aunt</l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41">Leonella, they left behind them the holy remembrance</l>
      <l n="42"></l>
      <l n="43">of their martyrdom ; and I pray that they may bestow</l>
      <l n="44"></l>
      <l n="45">upon my unworthy self, and upon our holy father, the</l>
      <l n="46">beneﬁt of their intercession and protection.</l>
      <l n="47"></l>
      <l n="48"></l>
      <l n="49"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p393">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">QUEM DE OPUSCULIS MAJORUM ABBREVIANDO</l>
      <l n="3">BEDA COMPOSUIT.</l>
      <l n="4"></l>
      <l n="5">CAP. I.—DE SITU HIERUSALEM.</l>
      <l n="6"></l>
      <l n="7">- ITUS urbis Hierusalem pene in</l>
      <l n="8">orbem circumactus, non parvo mu-</l>
      <l n="9">‘ rorum ambitu assurgit, quo etiam</l>
      <l n="10"></l>
      <l n="11">3 tus pro arce urbi supereminet, et</l>
      <l n="12">x 3" major pars civitatis infra montem</l>
      <l n="13"></l>
      <l n="14">jacet, in planitie humilioris collis</l>
      <l n="15"></l>
      <l n="16">sita. Post passionem quippe Domini a Tito impe-</l>
      <l n="17">ratore destructa, sed ab Elio Hadriano Cæsare, a quo</l>
      <l n="18">etiam Elia nunc vocatur, instaurata multoque amplior</l>
      <l n="19">eﬂ'ecta est. Unde est, quod cum Dominus extra portas</l>
      <l n="20">urbis passus sepultusque sit, modo loca passionis et</l>
      <l n="21">resurrectionis illius intra ejusdem mænia cernantur,</l>
      <l n="22">cujus in magno murorum ambitu octoginta quatuor</l>
      <l n="23">turres, portæ vero sex visuntur. Prima porta David</l>
      <l n="24"></l>
      <l n="25">ad occidentem montis Sion: secunda porta vallis Ful-</l>
      <l n="26"></l>
      <l n="27"></l>
      <l n="28"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p394">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">OF</l>
      <l n="3"></l>
      <l n="4">THE HOLY PLACES,</l>
      <l n="5"></l>
      <l n="6">ABRIDGED BY BEDE FROM THE WORKS OF THE</l>
      <l n="7">ANCIENTS.</l>
      <l n="8"></l>
      <l n="9">CHAP. I.—0F JERUSALEM.</l>
      <l n="10"></l>
      <l n="11">HE city of Jerusalem is almost</l>
      <l n="12"></l>
      <l n="13">circular in its form, and the com-</l>
      <l n="14"></l>
      <l n="15">' pass of its walls is by no means</l>
      <l n="16">inconsiderable, and formerly in-</l>
      <l n="17"></l>
      <l n="18">~ 3Q eluded Mount Sion, which is close</l>
      <l n="19">, ;'&amp;x' by, towards the south, and looks</l>
      <l n="20">5- -;; like the citadel of the town. The</l>
      <l n="21">greater part of the city is lower</l>
      <l n="22"></l>
      <l n="23">than the mountain,fand lies on the plain summit of one</l>
      <l n="24">of the lower hills in the neighbourhood. Aﬁer our</l>
      <l n="25">Lord’s passion it was destroyed by the Emperor Titus;</l>
      <l n="26">but was restored and enlarged by Allius Hadrianus</l>
      <l n="27">Cæsar, from whom it received the name of Elia. This</l>
      <l n="28">is the reason why the place where our Lord suﬂ'ered</l>
      <l n="29">and was buried is now within the walls, whereas it was</l>
      <l n="30">' at that time without. In the circumference of its walls,</l>
      <l n="31">which is extensive, there are eighty—four towers and six</l>
      <l n="32">gates. The ﬁrst is David’s gate, to the west of Mount</l>
      <l n="33">Sion: the second is the gate of the Fuller’s Valley: the</l>
      <l n="34"></l>
      <l n="35">:i</l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37">&amp;</l>
      <l n="38">xxi</l>
      <l n="39">(,.</l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41"></l>
      <l n="42"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p395">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">lonis: tertia porta Sancti Stephani: quarta porta Ben-</l>
      <l n="3">jamin: quinta portula, id est, parvula porta, ab hac per</l>
      <l n="4">gradus ad vallem Josaphat descenditur: sexta porta</l>
      <l n="5">Thecuitis. Celebriores tamen ex his sunt tres exitus</l>
      <l n="6">portarum: unus quidem ab occasu, alius a septentrione,</l>
      <l n="7">tertius ab oriente. A meridie autem, aquilonale montis</l>
      <l n="8">Sion supercilium supereminet civitati, et ea pars mu-</l>
      <l n="9">rorum cum interpositis turribus nullas habere portas</l>
      <l n="10">comprobatur, id est, a suprascripta David porta, usque</l>
      <l n="11">ad eam montis Sion frontem, quæ prærupta rupe orien-</l>
      <l n="12">talem respicit plagam. Situs quippe ipsius urbis a</l>
      <l n="13">supercilio aquilonali montis Sion incipiens, ita est</l>
      <l n="14">molli clivo dispositus, usque ad humiliora aquilonalium</l>
      <l n="15">orientaliumque loca murorum, ut pluvia ibi decidens</l>
      <l n="16">nequaquam stet, sed instar fluviorum per orientales</l>
      <l n="17">defluens portas, cunctis secum platearum sordibus</l>
      <l n="18">raptis, in valle J osaphat torrentem Cedron auget.</l>
      <l n="19"></l>
      <l n="20">CAP. II--DE LOCIS SANCTIS QUJE IN EA SITA</l>
      <l n="21">SUNT.</l>
      <l n="22"></l>
      <l n="23">NGRESSIS ergo &amp; septentrionali</l>
      <l n="24"></l>
      <l n="25">‘— parte urbem, primum de locis</l>
      <l n="26"></l>
      <l n="27">sanctis pro conditione platearum</l>
      <l n="28"></l>
      <l n="29">divcrtcndum est ad ecclesiam Con—</l>
      <l n="30"></l>
      <l n="31">: stantinianam, quæ Martyrium ap-</l>
      <l n="32"></l>
      <l n="33">]! ' pellatur. Hanc Constantinus Im-</l>
      <l n="34"></l>
      <l n="35">‘5 perator, eo quod ibi crux Domini</l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37">ab Helena matre reperta sit, mag-</l>
      <l n="38"></l>
      <l n="39">nifico et regio cultu construxit. Dehinc ab occasu</l>
      <l n="40">Golgothana videtur ecclesia, in qua etiam rupes ap-</l>
      <l n="41">paret illa, quæ quondam ipsam, aﬂixo Domini corpore, '</l>
      <l n="42">crucem pertulit, argenteam modo pergrandem susti-</l>
      <l n="43">nens crucem, pendente magna desuper ærea rota cum</l>
      <l n="44">lampadibus. Infra ipsum vero locum Dominicæ crucis,</l>
      <l n="45"></l>
      <l n="46"></l>
      <l n="47"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p396">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">third is St. Stephen’s gate: the fourth, Benjamin’s:</l>
      <l n="3"></l>
      <l n="4">the ﬁfth is the Postem or little gate, through which we</l>
      <l n="5"></l>
      <l n="6">go down by steps to the Valley of Jehoshaphat: the</l>
      <l n="7"></l>
      <l n="8">sixth gate is called Thecuitis. The most celebrated of</l>
      <l n="9">these are the three gates of egress; the ﬁrst towards</l>
      <l n="10"></l>
      <l n="11">the west, the second towards the north, and the third</l>
      <l n="12"></l>
      <l n="13">towards the east. On the south the northern brow of</l>
      <l n="14">Mount Sion appears above the city; and this part of</l>
      <l n="15">the walls, with the interposing towers, is proved to have</l>
      <l n="16"></l>
      <l n="17">had no gates ; namely, from David’s gate above-men-</l>
      <l n="18"></l>
      <l n="19">tioned, to that front of Mount Sion which looks with a</l>
      <l n="20"></l>
      <l n="21">rugged precipice towards the east. For the position of ~</l>
      <l n="22">the city itself is this: it begins from the northern brow</l>
      <l n="23"></l>
      <l n="24">of Mount Sion, and falls with a gentle slope towards</l>
      <l n="25"></l>
      <l n="26">the walls on the north-east, where it is lower, so that</l>
      <l n="27"></l>
      <l n="28">the rain which falls runs in streams through the eastern</l>
      <l n="29"></l>
      <l n="30">gates, and carries with it all the ﬁlth of the streets into</l>
      <l n="31"></l>
      <l n="32">the brook Cedron, in the Valley of J ehoshaphat.</l>
      <l n="33"></l>
      <l n="34">CHAP. IL—OF THE HOLY PLACES IN IT.</l>
      <l n="35"></l>
      <l n="36">WHEN you have entered the city on the northern</l>
      <l n="37">side, ﬁrst of the holy places, as regards the order of</l>
      <l n="38">the streets, you must turn out of the way to see the</l>
      <l n="39">church of Constantine, which is called the Martyrdom.</l>
      <l n="40">It was built in the most magniﬁcent and princely style</l>
      <l n="41">by the Emperor Constantine, to commemorate the ﬁnd-</l>
      <l n="42">ing of our Lord’s cross in this place by his mother</l>
      <l n="43">Helena. To the west of this is seen the church of</l>
      <l n="44">Golgotha, where too may be seen the rock which for-</l>
      <l n="45">merly bore the very cross that was fastened to our</l>
      <l n="46">Lord’s body; but which now bears a very large silver</l>
      <l n="47">cross, and a great wheel of brass hangs from above with</l>
      <l n="48">lamps. Under the place of our Lord’s cross, a vault is</l>
      <l n="49"></l>
      <l n="50"></l>
      <l n="51"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p397">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">excisa in petra crypta est, in qua super altare pro</l>
      <l n="3">defunctis honoratis sacrificium solet offerri, positis</l>
      <l n="4">interim in platea corporibus. Hujus quoque ad oc-</l>
      <l n="5">casum ecclesiæ Anastasia, hoc est, resurrectionis Domi-</l>
      <l n="6">nicæ rotunda ecclesia, tribus cincta parietibus, duo-</l>
      <l n="7">decim columnis sustentatur, inter parietes singulos</l>
      <l n="8">latum habens spatium viæ, quæ tria. altaria. in tribus</l>
      <l n="9">locis parietis medii continet, hoc est, australi, aquilonali,</l>
      <l n="10">et occidentali. Hæc bis quaternas portas, id est, in-</l>
      <l n="11">troitus per tres e regione parietes habet, e quibus qua-</l>
      <l n="12">tuor ad Vulturnum, et quatuor ad Eurum spectant.</l>
      <l n="13">Hujus in medio monumentum Domini rotundum petra</l>
      <l n="14">excisum est, cujus culmen intrinsecus stans homo</l>
      <l n="15">manu contingere potest, ab oriente habens introitum,</l>
      <l n="16">cui lapis ille magnus appositus est, quod intrinsecus</l>
      <l n="17">ferramentorum vestigia usque in præsens ostendunt.</l>
      <l n="18">Nam extrinsecus usque ad culminis summitatem totum</l>
      <l n="19">marmore tectum est; summum verO- culmen auro</l>
      <l n="20">ornatum, auream magnam gestat crucem. In hujus</l>
      <l n="21">ergo monumenti aquilonali parte sepulchrum Domini</l>
      <l n="22">in eadem petra excisum, longitudinis septem pedum,</l>
      <l n="23">trium mensura palmarum pavimento altius eminet, in-</l>
      <l n="24">troitum habens a latere meridiano: ubi die noctuque</l>
      <l n="25">duodecim lampades ardent, quatuor intra sepulchrum,</l>
      <l n="26">octo supra in margine dextro. Lapis qui ad ostium</l>
      <l n="27">monumenti positus erat, nunc fissus est; cujus pars</l>
      <l n="28">minor quadratum altare ante ostium nihilominus ejus-</l>
      <l n="29">dem monumenti stat, major vero in orientali ejusdem</l>
      <l n="30">ecclesiæ loco quadrangulum aliud altare sub linteami-</l>
      <l n="31">nibus extat. Color autem ejusdem monumenti, et</l>
      <l n="32">sepulchri, albo et rubicundo permixtus videtur. A</l>
      <l n="33">dextra autem parte huic ecclesiæ cohaeret beatæ Domini</l>
      <l n="34">Genitricis ecclesia quadrangula. In platea, quæ marty-</l>
      <l n="35">rium et Golgotha continuat, exedra est, in qua calix</l>
      <l n="36">Domini in scriniolo reconditus, per operculi foramen</l>
      <l n="37">tangi solet et osculari. Qui argenteus calix, duas</l>
      <l n="38">hinc et inde habens ansulas, sextarii Gallici men-</l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p398">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">hewn out of the rock, in which sacriﬁce is offered on</l>
      <l n="3">an altar for honourable persons deceased, their bodies</l>
      <l n="4">remaining meanwhile in the street. To the westward</l>
      <l n="5">of this is the Anastasis, that is, the round church of our</l>
      <l n="6">Saviour’s resurrection, encompassed with three walls,</l>
      <l n="7">and supported by twelve columns. Between each of</l>
      <l n="8">the walls is a broad space, containing three altars at</l>
      <l n="9">three different points of the middle wall, on the north,</l>
      <l n="10">the south, and the west. It has eight doors or en-</l>
      <l n="11">trances through the three opposite walls; four whereof</l>
      <l n="12">front to the north-east, and four to the south-east. In</l>
      <l n="13">the midst of it is the round tomb of our Lord cut out</l>
      <l n="14">of the rock, the top of which a man standing within can</l>
      <l n="15">touch; the entrance is on the east; against it is laid</l>
      <l n="16">that great stone, which to this day bears the marks of</l>
      <l n="17">the iron tools within, but on the outside it is all covered</l>
      <l n="18">with marble to the very top of the roof, which is</l>
      <l n="19">adorned with gold, and bears &amp; large golden cross. In</l>
      <l n="20">the north part of the monument is the tomb of our</l>
      <l n="21">Lord, hewn out of the same rock, seven feet in length,</l>
      <l n="22">and three palms above the ﬂoor; the entrance being on</l>
      <l n="23">the south side, where twelve lamps bum day and night,</l>
      <l n="24">four within the sepulchre, and eight above on the right-</l>
      <l n="25">hand side. The stone that was laid a't the entrance to</l>
      <l n="26">the monument is now cleft in two; the lesser part of it</l>
      <l n="27">stands as a square altar before the door of the monu-</l>
      <l n="28">ment; the greater part makes another square altar in</l>
      <l n="29">the east part of the same church, and appears under the</l>
      <l n="30">linen cloths. The colour of the said monument and</l>
      <l n="31">sepulchre appears to be white and red. Attached to</l>
      <l n="32">this church on the right side is the square church of</l>
      <l n="33">the blessed Mother of our Lord. In the street which</l>
      <l n="34">unites the Martyrdom and the Golgotha is a seat, in</l>
      <l n="35">which is the cup of our Lord concealed in a casket. It</l>
      <l n="36">is touched and kissed through a hole in the covering.</l>
      <l n="37">It is made of silver, has two handles, one on each side,</l>
      <l n="38">and holds a French 'quart. In it also is the sponge</l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p399">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">suram capit: in quo est et illa spongia Dominici potus</l>
      <l n="3">ministra. In loco autem illo, quo Abraham altare ad</l>
      <l n="4">immolandum filium construxit, mensa est lignea non</l>
      <l n="5">parva, in quam pauperum eleemosynæ solent a populo</l>
      <l n="6">deferri. Lancea militis inserta habetur in cruce lignea</l>
      <l n="7">in porticu martyrii, cujus hastile in duas intercisum</l>
      <l n="8">partes, a tota veneratur civitate. Singula quæ dixi,</l>
      <l n="9"></l>
      <l n="10">ut manifestius agnosceres, etiam præ oculis depingere</l>
      <l n="11">curavi.</l>
      <l n="12"></l>
      <l n="13">(Deest ﬁyura in MSS.)</l>
      <l n="14"></l>
      <l n="15">Hæc quidem omnia quæ commemoravimus sancta</l>
      <l n="16">loca, extra montem Sion posita cernuntur, quo se ad</l>
      <l n="17">aquilonem deficiens loci tumor porrexit. In inferiori</l>
      <l n="18">vero parte urbis, ubi templum in vicinia muri ab oriente</l>
      <l n="19">locatum, ipsique urbi, transitum pervio ponte mediante,</l>
      <l n="20">fuerat conjunctum, nunc Saraceni quadratam domum</l>
      <l n="21">subrectis tabulis et magnis trabibus super quasdam rui-</l>
      <l n="22"></l>
      <l n="23">narum reliquias vili opere construentes, oratione frequen-</l>
      <l n="24">tant, quæ tria millia hominum capere videtur. Paucæ</l>
      <l n="25">illic cisbemæ in usum aquarum cernuntur. In vicinia</l>
      <l n="26">templi Bethsaida piscina gemino insignis lacu apparet,</l>
      <l n="27">quorum alter hybemis plerumque impletur imbribus,</l>
      <l n="28">alter mbris est discolor aquis. Ab ea fronte montis</l>
      <l n="29">Sion, quæ prærupta rupe orientalem plagam spectat,</l>
      <l n="30">intra muros atque in radicibus collis fons Siloe prorum-</l>
      <l n="31">pit, qui alternante quidem aquarum accessu in meri-</l>
      <l n="32">dem defluit, id est, non certis vel jugibus aquis, sed</l>
      <l n="33">incertis horis diebusque ebullit, et per terrarum con-</l>
      <l n="34">cava et antra saxi durissimi cum magno sonitu venire</l>
      <l n="35">consuevit. In superiori montis Sion" planitie, mona-</l>
      <l n="36">chorum cellulæ frequentes ecclesiam magnam circum-</l>
      <l n="37">dant, illic, ut perhibent, ab Apostolis fundatam, eo</l>
      <l n="38"></l>
      <l n="39"></l>
      <l n="40"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p400">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">which was used to minister drink to our Lord. But</l>
      <l n="3">where Abraham built an altar whereon to sacriﬁce his</l>
      <l n="4">son, there is a large wooden table, on which the people</l>
      <l n="5">lay alms for the poor. The soldier’s lance also is kept</l>
      <l n="6">inserted in a wooden cross, in the portico of the Mar-</l>
      <l n="7">tyrdom, and its shaft, which has been broken in two</l>
      <l n="8">pieces, is an object of veneration to the whole city. All</l>
      <l n="9">these particulars, which I have here mentioned, I have</l>
      <l n="10">endeavoured to render more intelligible by the follow-</l>
      <l n="11">ing,picture.</l>
      <l n="12">(The drawing is wanting in the Manmcripta.)</l>
      <l n="13"></l>
      <l n="14">Now all these holy places, which we have men-</l>
      <l n="15">tioned, are situated beyond Mount Sion, to which the</l>
      <l n="16">elevated ground extends as it falls away towards the</l>
      <l n="17">north. But in the lower part of the city, where there</l>
      <l n="18">was a temple built in the neighbourth of the wall, on</l>
      <l n="19">the eastern side, and joined to the city itself by a bridge</l>
      <l n="20">which formed a thoroughfare between, the Saracens</l>
      <l n="21">have now erected there a square building, with upright</l>
      <l n="22">planks and large beams placed, in the roughest manner,</l>
      <l n="23">over some ruins of the walls, and they frequent the</l>
      <l n="24">place for prayer. There is room for three thousand</l>
      <l n="25">persons. There are a few cisterns there to supply</l>
      <l n="26">water. In the neighbourhood of the temple is the pool</l>
      <l n="27">of Bethsaida, marked by its two basins, one of which is</l>
      <l n="28">generally ﬁlled by the rains of winter, the other is dis—</l>
      <l n="29">coloured with red water. On that front of Mount Sion</l>
      <l n="30">which has a rugged precipice facing the east, the foun-</l>
      <l n="31">tain of Siloa bursts forth between the walls at the</l>
      <l n="32">bottom of the hill. According as it receives an in-</l>
      <l n="33">crease of water from time to time, it ﬂows towards the</l>
      <l n="34">south; therefore its waters are not sweet, but the day</l>
      <l n="35">and hour of its springing up are uncertain, and it</l>
      <l n="36">rushes with much noise amid the hollows in the ground</l>
      <l n="37">and the hard rocks. On the level summit of Mount</l>
      <l n="38">Sion are numerous cells of monks surrounding a large</l>
      <l n="39">church, built there, as they say, by the Apostles, be-</l>
      <l n="40"></l>
      <l n="41">D d</l>
      <l n="42"></l>
      <l n="43"></l>
      <l n="44"></l>
    </page>
    <page n="GILES v04.p401">
      <headline/>
      <l n="1"></l>
      <l n="2">quod ibi Spiritum Sanctum acceperint, ibique S. Maria</l>
      <l n="3">obierit. In qua etiam locus cænæ Domini venerabilis</l>
      <l n="4">ostenditur. Sed et columna marmorea in medio stat</l>
      <l n="5">ecclesiæ, cui adhærens Dominus flagellatus est. Hujus</l>
      <l n="6"></l>
      <l n="7">ergo ecclesiæ talis dicitur esse figura.</l>
      <l n="8">(Deest figura in MSS.)</l>
      <l n="9"></l>
      <l n="10">Hic monstratur petra, super quam lapidatus est</l>
      <l n="11">sanctus protomartyr Stephanus extra civitatem. In</l>
      <l n="12">medio autem Hierusalem, ubi cruce Domini superposita</l>
      <l n="13">mortuus revixit, columna celsa stat, quæ æstivo sol-</l>
      <l n="14">stitio umbram non facit, unde putant ibi mediam esse</l>
      <l n="15">terram, et historice dictum: ‘Deus autem ante secula</l>
      <l n="16">operatus est salutem in medio terræ., Qua ductus</l>
      <l n="17">opinione Victorinus Pictaviensis, antistes ecclesiæ, de</l>
      <l n="18">Golgotha scribens ita inchoat:</l>
      <l n="19"></l>
      <l n="20">‘ Est locus, ex omni medium quem credimus orbe,</l>
      <l n="21"></l>
      <l n="22">Golgotha Judæi patrio cognomine dicunt.,</l>
      <l n="23"></l>
      <l n="24">CAP. III.—-DE ACHELDEMACH, ET LOCO UBI sus-v</l>
      <l n="25">PENSUS EST JUDAS.</l>
      <l n="26"></l>
      <l n="27">PORTAM David egredientibus, fons occurrit in aus-</l>
      <l n="28">trum per vallem directus, ad cujus medietatem ab</l>
      <l n="29">occasu Judas se suspendisse narratur. Nam et ficus</l>
      <l n="30"></l>
      <l n="31">magna ibi, ac vetustissima stat, juxta quod Juvencus</l>
      <l n="32">ait:</l>
      <l n="33"></l>
      <l n="34">‘ Informem rapuit ﬁcus de vertice mortem.,</l>
      <l n="35"></l>
      <l n="36"></l>
      <l n="37"></l>
    </page>
  </body>
</xml>
